<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A consolacyon for chrysten people to repayre agayn the lordes temple with certayne places of scrypture truely applyed to satysfye theyr myndes for ye expellyng of ydolatry, [et] to instruct the[m], of loue and obedience. Compyled by nycholas wyse</title>
            <author>Wyse, Nicholas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1538</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 134 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 71 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15802</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 26063</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105455</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841183</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841183</idno>
            <idno type="VID">5745</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15802)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5745)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 303:24)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A consolacyon for chrysten people to repayre agayn the lordes temple with certayne places of scrypture truely applyed to satysfye theyr myndes for ye expellyng of ydolatry, [et] to instruct the[m], of loue and obedience. Compyled by nycholas wyse</title>
                  <author>Wyse, Nicholas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[144] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Iohn Waylande with in Temple barre at the sygne of the blewe garland,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprynted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno .M.D.xxxviii. the .xvi. day of Octobre.] [1538]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: [A]-I.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; lacks leaves I3 and I4.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:5745:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5745:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>¶A conſolacyon for chryſten people to repayre agayn the lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des temple, with cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne places of ſcryp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture truely applyed to ſatyſfye theyr myndes for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> expellyng of ydo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, &amp; to inſtruct the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, of loue and obedience.</p>
            <p>Compyled By nycholas wyſe</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:5745:2"/>
            <head>¶A preface of the prophetes.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>The prophet Eſay made an exclamacyon</l>
               <l>That heuen and erthe ſhulde herken to the lorde</l>
               <l>whiche for the peoples great abhomynacyon</l>
               <l>Prouokyng hym to angre dyſpleaſure and dyſcorde</l>
               <l>Theyr faſtynges / theyr prayers / &amp; offrynges he abhor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>yet mercyfully exhortyng them to mende &amp; to lyue well</l>
               <l>He promyſed them pardon theyr ſynnes for to expell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶The prophet Ieremy elected was of god</l>
               <l>And ſanctefyed before that he was borne</l>
               <l>Commaunded to threten the people with his rod</l>
               <l>And fearfull plages on cattell, graſſe, and corne</l>
               <l>With other punyſſhmentes to cauſe them for to morne</l>
               <l>Declaryng theyr captyuyte theyr paynes &amp; cruell bandes</l>
               <l>To come for theyr ſynne and ydols made with handes</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶The prophet Oſeas lykewyſe dyd prophecy</l>
               <l>Agaynſt the preeſtes that people do dyſceyue</l>
               <l>And alſo rebuked Iſraell and Samary</l>
               <l>For theyr ydolatry / but they wolde not receyue</l>
               <l>Goddes grace &amp; promyſes / nor his ſwete wordes conceyue</l>
               <l>They were vnthankfull, wherfore he dyd them blame</l>
               <l>Recytyng theyr ſynne and punyſſhment for the ſame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶The prophet Aggeus, came to zorobabell</l>
               <l>The prynce of Iuda declaryng hym the wyll</l>
               <l>Of god the lorde, whoſe goodneſſe dothe excell</l>
               <l>Exortyng the people his pleaſure to fulfyll</l>
               <l>Rebukyng theyr ſlackneſſe as it was ryght and ſkyll</l>
               <l>For that they applyed not theyr bodyes to ſome payne</l>
               <l>Theyr temple dyſtroyed for to buylde vp agayne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:5745:2"/>
               <l>¶The prophet Mycheas reproued the wyckedneſſe</l>
               <l>Of them that inclyned vnto ydolatry</l>
               <l>Expreſſyng the payne for theyr vngodlyneſſe</l>
               <l>Reherſyng theyr ſynne, and yf I ſhulde not lye</l>
               <l>The cauſe he expounded of theyr myſery</l>
               <l>Aledgyng it to rulers whiche trouthe dyd not regarde</l>
               <l>And vnto preeſtes that preache for profyte and rewarde</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶The prophet zachary ſpake by the ſpyryte of grace</l>
               <l>Comfortyng the people to tourne vnto the lorde</l>
               <l>whiche for theyr offences dyſperſed were longe ſpace</l>
               <l>Among the hethen the ſcrypture to recorde</l>
               <l>But god purpoſyng that they ſhulde be reſtored</l>
               <l>Out of thraldome as ſtoryes do me tell</l>
               <l>Delyuered the people of Iude and Iſraell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶The prophet Malachy ſpake of the ioyfull day</l>
               <l>Of Chryſtes comyng the people for to ſaue</l>
               <l>And alſo of hym that ſhulde prepare his way</l>
               <l>Expreſſyng the pleaſure that godly men ſhulde haue</l>
               <l>As for the vngodly he greatly dothe depraue</l>
               <l>Declaryng theyr dyuerſytes through god omnipotent</l>
               <l>And theyr vnlyke rewardes whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſhall gyue iudgement.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶Chryſt the true prophet and lorde of prophetes all</l>
               <l>Of whom the prophetes before dyd prohcey</l>
               <l>Beyng the only ſonne of god celeſtyall</l>
               <l>Approued the prophetes, theyr prophecyes he dyd verefy</l>
               <l>For he of whom they prophecyed the worlde to iuſtify</l>
               <l>Performed theyr prophecyes, from heuen he dyſcended</l>
               <l>His fathers wyll fulfylled, and vp agayne aſcended.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>¶In regnum dei.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="prologue">
            <pb facs="tcp:5745:3"/>
            <head>¶The prologue.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Onſidering in my mynd the great decay of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes churche that hathe contynewed of a longe ſeaſon (beynge the fayth<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful congregacyon,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Cor vi</note> which Paule cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth his temple.) It hath impelled me of a true &amp; vnfayned herte to take payne (as the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon ſayeng is) wher at mought more truely be counted a pleaſure, to wryte this litel volume. But for as moche as I ſtode in ſtay and doubted the iudgementes of the vnlearned multitude lackynge yet knowledge to deſerne the ſpirituall lyght from darkeneſſe, ye &amp; not that onely, but alſo doubted the iudgmen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes of ſuche as haue lernyng, which in tyme paſt feared not to peruerte y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcriptures. Truely it troubled ſo my mynde, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> I was in .xx. wyttes whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:5745:3"/> I mought ſet forthe this worke acordyng to my fyrſt purpoſe, eyther els let fall my labours, kepyng it ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret to my ſelfe and takyng onely to my rewarde my payne for my trauel. Thus ſtageryng as a man beyng in an open, large, and wylde foreſt kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyng not whiche waye to reſorte or ryde to his lodgyng, ſometyme fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng the vncertaynty of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> way, ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyme doubtyng whether y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ende of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> way dyd lede vnto a wood or couert full of buſſhes and bryers, ſomtyme fearynge robbers, theues, and cruell beaſtes to ſpoyle and deuoure hym. And laſt of all fearyng leſt the nyght ſhulde come vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him before he came to his iourneys ende. So I beynge in this ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> foreſt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde though I knowe the way of the ſcrypture to be certayne, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ende therof to lede to quietnes and reſt, and that it is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> onely rule for all men to frame theyr workes thervnto. By the which rule
<pb facs="tcp:5745:4"/> I haue facyoned &amp; framed this wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke (as nere as God hathe gyuen me grace. yet I doubted the vncertayne Iudgementes of other men, the one ſorte that knowe not the waye, &amp; the other ſorte knowyng it hauynge no pleaſure to walke therin, taking vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them to be guydes vnto the ſymple &amp; vnlerned. Where in very dede many of them haue rather played the part of cruyll ſpoylers and deuourers as it may appere to all the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it hathe pleaſed god, eyther to preſerue from ſpoylyng or els of his infinyte good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, to call &amp; conducte from falſe &amp; fayned pathes, vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true &amp; perfyte way which Chriſt hath apoynted vs to walke in. Vnto the whiche way to conforte, counſell, &amp; courage all men. I haue applyed this my labour, fyrſt to conforte them in the trueth, to cou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rage them to ſtycke vnto the trueth, &amp; to counſel them to folowe the ſame<note place="margin">i. cor vi. ii. cor. vi</note> that the lordes temple may be reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb facs="tcp:5745:4"/> and repayred agayne. But after my labours ended, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thynge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hathe incouraged me to ſet forth my good wyll vnto all men (beyng in this ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny doubtes &amp; troubles of mynde) I wyll ſhewe you. I counſayled w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> my ſelfe and yf it were beſt for me to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate it vnto ſome noble man, as ye may ſe in dyuers prefaces &amp; prolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of bokes, ſome are dedycated vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to one man, and ſome vnto an other, whiche thyng truely I wolde that al men dyd no leſſe prayſe &amp; alowe then my ſelfe, for it is an occaſion to al the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which vnfaynedly bere louyng myn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des vnto the perſon whom the thyng is dedicated to haue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> more fauoure and loue vnto it, and to be the more deſyrous to rede &amp; peruſe it for his ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke. But as there is in this worlde no pleaſure without payne, no conforte without care, no ioy without ſorowe and to be ſhort nothyng without his contrary. So in this I was not ſo
<pb facs="tcp:5745:5"/> moch incouraged forwarde one way but I was more dyſcouraged back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde an other way. For when I cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led to my remembraunce y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> frowarde ymagynacyons and vntrewe repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of ſuche as be euyll whiche alſo haue ceduſed the poore and vnlerned to thynke all thyng to be as true as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpell y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſpeake my herte was quyte diſcouraged to dedycate it vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to any noble man. The lacke of elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence to ſet forth this worke and to make it more mete and conuenyent to be preſented vnto ſuche an eſtate or perſon (for as moche as I haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pared and framed it to the infallible truthe of goddes bleſſed worde) dyd lytell or nothyng dyſcomforte me. But becauſe I wolde not haue the truthe to be ſclaundered by the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lycyous tonges of thoſe that wolde ſaye. This felowe hath taken payne to ſet forth a worke to pleaſe ſuche a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> withal. I was at a playne poynt
<pb facs="tcp:5745:5"/> with my ſelfe to kepe it vndefamed that waye, and not onely to ſaue the truthe from falſe ſuſpicion, but ſuche perſons alſo from offendyng y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wold vntruely reporte it. For it is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted that many whiche haue not feared to ſpeake euyll of the goſpell, (ſayeng it wold make me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heretykes) wold not paſſe vpon the ſclaundryng of ony good purpoſe or <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>tence of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Thus wayeng the matter as it were in a ballaunce, I perceyued yet in all thynges that the truthe ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cometh at length, and then conſyde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng the ioyful and acceptable tyme that is nowe,<note place="margin">ii. cor. vi.</note> ſo that the euangelycal lyght ſhyneth ouer vs,<note place="margin">Ro. xiii.</note> the nyght be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng paſt and the daye come to gyue lyght vnto al men that lyſt to labour in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lordes worke, it entred in to my herte (thoughe I myſtruſted not the comyng of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nyght agayne) yet that I ought not to be neglygent in the lordes worke accordyng to the gyfte
<pb facs="tcp:5745:6"/> which is gyue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me. But whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I coulde fynde nothyng to quyet my mynde for the ſettyng forth therof, without the daunger of ſome euyll reporte, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worde of god (beynge the true ſalue for all maner of ſores, and the perfyt medeſyne for all maner ſpiritual diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes) gaue me comforte prouokyng me to ſtay no longer therin by the pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rable of certayne men whiche recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of their lord and mayſter ſundry talentes to be put in vſe for his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntage vntyll his retourne out of a ſtraunge countre, in to the whiche he toke his iourney. And after a long ſeaſon the lorde of thoſe ſeruauntes came and rekened with them. Then he that had receyued .v. talentes ſaid mayſter thou delyueredeſt vnto me v.<note place="margin">mat. xxv</note> talentes, beholde I haue gayned with them .v. talentes mo. Then his mayſter ſayd vnto hym, well good ſeruaunt and faythful, thou haſt ben faythfull in lytell, I wyl conſtitute y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:5745:6"/> ouer moche, entre in to thy mayſters ioy. And he that had receyued .ii. ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentes had gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> other .ii. vnto who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lyke anſwere was made. But the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunt whiche had receyued but one talent and applyed it to no profyte, but hyd it in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> erthe came and ſayd. Mayſter I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſydered that thou waſt an harde man, whiche repeſt where thou ſoweſt not, and gathered where thou ſtroweſt not, wherfore I was afrayde beholde, y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſt thyne awne. But for his ſlouthfull and euyll ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyce he was rebuked, his talent ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from hym and gyuen to hym y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> had many, and the vnprofytable ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunt caſt in to vtter darknes. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I remembred this ſayeng of the lord which haue receyued but one ſymple talent in comparyſon of other which haue applyed their wyttes and ler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng to fulfyl the lordes pleaſure as it appereth by their excellent workes and bokes that they haue wrytten,
<pb facs="tcp:5745:7"/> yet feryng leſt this ſmal talent ſhuld be taken from me, and ſo to receyue the dyſpleaſure of my lorde, whiche ought more to be feared then the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſures and dyſprayſes of all men, and his fauour and loue more to be extemed deſyred and ſought for, then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fauour of all creatures. I thought it more conuenyent to folow his wyl then to regarde the falſe iudgemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes and the vntrue reportes of ſuche as knowe not the trouthe. And alſo of them whiche knowe it abuſynge theyr knowledge to theyr great dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and parell. Wherfore as one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendyng to ſaue al thyng as vpright as maye be, I haue attempted to ſet forth this my rude worke, beyng as the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon terme gothe as playne as a packe ſtaffe. And for it ſhall appere that I ſeke not the fauour of man, I haue not dedycate it vnto one man. But becauſe I wolde that all men ſhuld ſeke the fauour of god I haue
<pb facs="tcp:5745:7"/> dedycate it vnto all men, ye I wolde that the pooreſt begget whiche can rede or here it red ſhulde haue it. But whether they be poore or ryche, to whoſe handes this lytell boke ſhall happen to come I her<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ely deſyre the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not to ſtycke to any thyng whiche is here wrytten ferther then they ſhall thynke it approued by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcrypture &amp; word of god, &amp; as I haue wrytte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> boke folowing ſo I admonyſſhe you in this prologue before to take this worke for an exortacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort and counſell all men to rede and here the ſcrypture,<note place="margin">ephe. v.</note> that they may vnderſtand what the wyll of god is. And after y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they are ones called that they may la<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bour alſo to be choſen,<note place="margin">mat. xx. &amp; xxii.</note> for many are called and fewe be choſen. But ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly who ſoeuer be choſen wyll put to his helpynge handes for to repayre agayne the lordes temple whiche is not made w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> mennes handes.<note place="margin">act. xvii</note> I truſt in God to ſe this temple in his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feccyon
<pb facs="tcp:5745:8"/> that I maye reioyce as the people of Ieruſalem dyd at the repa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryng of the temple and cyte agayne.<note place="margin">i. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d. iii.</note> wherof ye ſhal perceyue more in this worke folowynge, vnto the whiche worke I haue cauſed my name to be ſet, not for any prayſe that I entende to ſeke therin, but for certayne conſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racyons mouynge me therunto. The one is that I haue herde by reporte of other men that diuers be offended with ſundry bokes, whiche beynge withoute name or aucthor haue ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther troubled theyr conſcyence then ſet it in a quyetneſſe, and that many haue ben ſuſpected to be doers therof whiche were neuer of counſell nor knowledge therin. And I maye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue the thyng to be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more true, for in a ſmall peice of worke or twayne whiche I haue ſet forth my ſelfe ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge it no certayne name, dyuers perſones of dyuers men haue had y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fame &amp; reporte to be doers of it. And
<pb facs="tcp:5745:8"/> though I paſſe not who haue the prayſe, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glory of god &amp; his truth may be roted &amp; take place in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hertes of men. yet as there is nothyng ſo ꝑ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyt, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> of ſome men it is diſpraiſed &amp; no meruayll ſeyng the very truthe (which is the worde of god) hath ben euyll reported of many. Therfore I thynke not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> any worke of man can content al men. And for theſe conſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deracyons w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> other neceſſari that I omyt I haue put vnto this my name as one being co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent to take diſprayſe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> prayſe, payne w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> pleaſure &amp; to be redy yf any faute ſhulde be to bere y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> burden therof my ſelfe as he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſecretes of mennes hertes be a wytnes &amp; iudge vnto me to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be honour praiſe &amp; glory for euer &amp; euer.<note place="margin">Sapi. i.</note> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>¶Finis.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>¶Theſe be the fautes eſcaped in the pryntynge. In the fyrſt page of B the .ix. lyne theſe for theyr. In the firſt page of E the xiiii. lyne lyberte for ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beralyte. In the .iiii. page of F the .xii. lyne of Chriſt In the .xiii. page .xvii. lyne of G the for theyr. And in the laſt page of the ſame ſay for lye,</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:5745:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5745:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hert way lyth not, whiche doth cogytate and remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre how vncharitably y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people of god haue bene dyſceaued &amp; that of no lytle tyme, through crafty ſcole maiſters. And falſe prechers.<note place="margin">Coll. ii.</note> which more regardynge the ſatyſfyenge of theſe deteſtable apetytes the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uacion of the precyous ſoules of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, haue kept the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from the trewe know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of his holy goſpell, that ſhulde inſtructe them the perfyte and redye way vnto hym, whiche ſayde.<note place="margin">Mat. xi Eccl. vi</note> Come vnto me all ye that laboure and are ladyn and I ſhall refreſſhe you.<note place="margin">i. Pe. ii. Eſa. liii</note> So that the people haue bene as ſhepe ſtrayeng in wildernes knowing not whyther to go.<note place="margin">Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. x Pro. xxxvii.</note> And yf ony hearyng the voyce of theyr trewe ſhepeherde, bega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to take y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtreyght pathe or way towardes hym,<note place="margin">mat. vii</note> there were a ſorte of rauenyng wolues alwayes wayting
<pb facs="tcp:5745:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> redye to rent and deuoure them, but oure mercyfull Chryſte beynge the good ſhepherde of his flocke.<note place="margin">Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. x Ezech. xxxiiii. Miche. v.</note> Nowe hauyng compaſſyon vpon the great dyſtruccyon of hys ſhepe. Sendes abrode his ſeruauntes and faythful mynyſters to ſeke and gather them whiche were ſcattered abrode, togy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers agayne / who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the wolffes and papyſtycall foxys dare not abyde to trye withall. But yet alas for pytye / ther is a great noumbre of Chryſtes flocke, whiche haue bene kepte ſo long from heryng the voyce of their ſhepherde, that ſcarſly they knowe hym,<note place="margin">Ioh. iiii</note> nowe callynge them vnto him. They ſtand in a ſtay dowtyng whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be he and his mynyſters that calles them or not. And ſome wyll harke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nothyng at al vnto his voyce, ſo that many ronne hedlynge ſtyl in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to ſuche ſnares as were inuented to take the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in. Whoſe myſerable eſtate I know not what to ſay vnto. What
<pb facs="tcp:5745:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> wold you that Chriſt ſhuld do more for you then he hathe done,<note place="margin">Ioh. iii. Rom. v i. Pe. iii</note> he hathe gyuen his lyfe for the redempcion of your ſoules, &amp; hath left vnto you his holy Teſtament that therin ye maye beholde and vnderſtande what hys godlye wyll is. And though it haue bene longe kept frome you. yet nowe of hys mercyfull goodnes ye haue fre lybertye to pervſe it. Alſo he hath apoynted vnto you true &amp; faythfull mynyſtres of his worde / with ſure &amp; ſtrong defenders / agaynſt ſuche as were wonte to be deuourers of his ſhepe. What thing els do you lacke / theſe thinges are the excellent giftes of the grace of god, and yf ye lacke grace &amp; ſtrength to come vnto hym / why call ye not for it. And aſke it of hym i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye haue a ꝓmyſe by chriſt that what ſo euer ye deſyre of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in his name / it ſhalbe gyuen you I meruayll ye conſyder and remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre not howe ſuche as toke on them<note place="margin">Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Mat. xxi. Mat. xi</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:5745:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> to be youre paſtours in tyme paſte haue pylled you. If ye wyll ſtyll fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low them / ye may well be reſembled to a frowarde or folyſſhe ſhepe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wyl ronne among the breres and rent y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> woll from his awne backe / or in to a dyke &amp; drowne hym ſelfe / your wyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes in this dothe appere to be no bet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter then a ſhepes wyt / god hathe gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen you the vſe of reaſon / &amp; to none other creature but vnto man onely. And for as moche as ye wyll obſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natly abuſe that noble and excellent gyfte / wherby onely ye excell y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> bruyt beaſtes. I can not ſe but your foly is inexcuſable. Thynke you it ſhall be a ſuffycyent excuſe for you to ſay / the byſſhops / the preeſtes / and ſuche as were our goſtly fathers taught vs this to do / &amp; our fathers this many yeres before vs haue folowed this way. Truely what way ſo euer your fathers folowed / yf it were not the ſame way / that chriſt apoynted them
<pb facs="tcp:5745:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> by his goſpell to walke in / without the great mercye of god be reſerued vnto them,<note place="margin">ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>v</note> the blynd folowers with the blynde guydes are fallen both in the pyt. Howbeit I ſuppoſe verely yf the goſpel of god had ben ſo prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chid vnto your fathers as it is vnto you, they wolde haue repented there yngnoraunces and iniquites moche more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> many do now at this tyme / ye and yf the goſpel myght haue had fre paſſage adn to be preached vnto all creatures as Cryſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded his dyſcyples to do,<note place="margin">Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> xvi. i Mat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> xxviii. Ioh. xi</note> I thynke verely that Idolatrye ſhulde neuer haue crepte in to the churche of Cryſt as it hath done. For it is to be ſuppoſed that when the biſſhop of Rome / with ſuche as pretended to be the ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours of Chriſt &amp; his appoſtles / dely<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted not in pouerte / but toke pleaſure in pryde, and coulde no longer away with the rule y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theyr mayſter Chryſt had preſcrybed vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / ſuppoſyng
<pb facs="tcp:5745:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> they ſhulde neuer attayne to be lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des and mayſters by that ſcyence. Then they layde theyr heddes togy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther howe they myght peruerte and ſuppreſſe the goſpell, and to oppreſſe all thoſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> contrary to theyr myndes wolde ſtycke ther vnto, then made they decreys and lawes to ſerue for theyr awne purpoſe, &amp; vnder a holy pretence ſet them forth to begyle the people withall. And when they had begyled kynges and prynces / &amp; ſuch as had theyr auctoryte by the worde of god. Then they ſone perſwaded y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> mooſt parte of the people therunto. And ſuche as wolde cleue to goddes goſpell / and not to theyr conſtytucy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons / were taken as heretykes and conſtrayned to adiure or to be brent. And when they had brought theyr purpoſe to paſſe ſomwhat according to theyr awne myndes / that the pryn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces and theyr people obeyed them. Then that antichryſt the byſſhop of
<pb facs="tcp:5745:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> Rome was not aſhamed to exempt hym ſelfe from all prynces lawes / &amp; to put the lawe and teſtament of the lorde god vnder his fote / as though god and man / heuen and earth had ben at his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement. But as for purgatory it was a palace of his awne / euery man knewe he mought do there what hym lyſt. And after he had (with the helpe of his louynge frendes) attayned to the glory of his vſurped papyſtycall power / yf any prynce began to w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>ſtand his wycked pleaſure out came the thonder bolte of exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municacion to interdicte both hym &amp; his realme / as the cronycles of Englande and Fraunce can ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyfy. It is no meruayle though our fore fathers haue ben diſceyued / and wandered in darkenes, ſeynge they were taught with blynd tradicions, &amp; the lyght of goddes word were ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Wherfore theyr foly is not ſo great in the ſyght of god, as
<pb facs="tcp:5745:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> ours,<note place="margin">Ephe. v</note> to whom the lyght is offered, &amp; do refuſe it. And as I ſayd before, I thynke that dyuers of our fathers wolde haue repented moche more, then many of vs do yf goddes word had ben ſo preached to them as it is vnto vs. I haue herde ſome aſke this queſtyon. We meruayle ſay they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this knowledge hath ben ſo longe kept fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs, &amp; fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our fathers i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tyme paſt this many yeres, and that it is now come to paſſe more then in an other tyme. This is a very dyffuſe queſtyon, howbeit ye ſhall here my mynde in it. ¶It is .v. or .vi. thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſande yeres paſt ſyns our fyrſt father Adam,<note place="margin">Ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. iii</note> tranſgreſſed the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Lorde for eatynge of the apple. And it is nowe but a. M D. xxxviii. yeres ſyns our ſauiour chriſt the ſeconde perſon in Trynyte ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red his paſſyon for the redempcyon of the ſynnes of all the world.<note place="margin">i. Pe. iii Rom<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> v Math. xxvii.</note> There were a great many of yeres from the
<pb facs="tcp:5745:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> tyme that Adam ſynned, vntyl chriſt payde the raunſome therof with his bloude, and many thouſandes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mytted ſynne in the meane ſeaſon be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore Chryſt came. Nowe yf any man coulde tell me why that Chriſt came no rather to redeme y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde, eyther why that he ſuffred more than, then at another tyme, me thynke I could anſwere the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dyrectly to their q<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtyon. ¶I can ſay no more but as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wyl of God the father was that his ſonne ſhulde then come to ſaue the people,<note place="margin">Luc. xix Ioh. iiii</note> whome Abraham, Iſaac, Iacob, nor any of all the holy fathers coulde ſaue (yet were they as holy as al the byſſhoppes of Rome that euer was) So is it his godly wyl that his holy goſpell whiche hath ben long kepte from vs, ſhulde nowe be preached a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne vnto vs. But to anſwere you why rather nowe then at an other tyme, or wherfore it hath ben ſo long kepte from vs.<note place="margin">Ro. xii. Eſa. xl.</note> I wyl ſay with ſaynt
<pb facs="tcp:5745:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> Paule (Quis enim cognouit ſenſum domini,<note place="margin">Rom xi. Eſa. xi. i. Co. ii.</note> aut quis conſiliatius eius fuit.) Who hath knowen the mynde of the lorde, or who was his counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers. Chriſt anſwered his diſciples that demaunded of hym, yf he wolde at that tyme ſet vp the kyngdom of Iſrael agayn, ſayeng.<note place="margin">Act. i. Mat. xxii i.</note> It belongeth not vnto you to know the tymes or ſeaſons which the father hath kepte in his awne power. It is not mete for men to ſerche out the ſecretes of god nor to be of his counſel. Perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture I coulde geſſe wherfore this knowledge hath ben taken awaye from the people, by other examples that I haue red in the hyſtoryes of the byble, of the chyldren of Iſraell, whiche often tymes forſoke the lawe of the lorde and fell to Idolatry, for the which they were punyſſhed with dyuers plages, and as long as their myndes were corrupted with Idola<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>try ſo long were theyr hertes &amp; theyr
<pb facs="tcp:5745:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> eyes blynded, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they had no power to herken nor loke on the law of the lorde. Idolatry lykewyſe I ſuppoſe hath ben the pryncypall cauſe that his goſpell and his holy worde hath ben taken away from vs.<note place="margin">i. Re. iii.</note> ¶Kynge Salomon y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was kyng ouer Iſraell and had ſuche wyſdome gyuen hym as neuer none had before hym, nor neuer ſhall haue after hym,<note place="margin">iii. re. vi</note> whiche buylded the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of god in Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as long as he walked in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wayes of the lorde al thynges dyd proſpere w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hym. In riches he dyd for his tyme excell all men. He had all the pleaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res that his herte lyked. But at laſt he abuſed the giftes of god, his wyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, his ryches,<note place="margin">iii. re. xi.</note> and fell to Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trye. He buylded hye houſes vnto Idolles, and folowed not the Lorde vnto the ende as his father Dauyd dyd. And then though the lorde ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red hym for his fathers ſake, yet fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his ſonne was there taken .x. trybes.
<pb facs="tcp:5745:15"/> And at lengthe from his poſteryte, whiche alſo fell vnto Idolatry, was taken the trybe of Iuda by the kyng of Babylon,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ii. Re. xxv.</note> the Cyte of Ieruſalem deſtroyed &amp; the temple of god beaten downe to the ground. And the kyng with the chefeſt of his people and all his riches led captyue in to babylon. But when it pleaſed god to haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſyon vpon his people, he delyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them agayne from they capty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyte, and brought them to the lande whiche he before had gyuen them to poſſeſſe, where they buylded agayne the temple and the Cyte of Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem that was dyſtroyed.<note place="margin">i. Eſd. iii.</note> And when they layde the foundacyon of the lor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des houſe they reioyſed with all me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lody, they conſydered the great mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy that God had done vnto them, &amp; gaue hym thankes. But alas the people now adayes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſyder not how they are delyuered out of Babylon, out of captyuyte and bondage from
<pb facs="tcp:5745:15"/> the byſſhop of Romes heuy trady<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyons, &amp; brought agayne to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyte lawe of lybertye, to the Goſpell of God that heuenly Ieruſalem. Where is the Ioy and melody that ye ſhuld make for your delyuerau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. Where is the thankes and prayſes that ye ſhulde gyue to God for his great mercy ſhewed vnto you. I thinke ye haue more feared y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> biſſhop of Romes curſes, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye now regard the bleſſyng of god fallen vpon you. With what bleſſynge wolde you ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecte, to be bleſſyd with all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> herte ought more to deſyre, then a re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy way vnto the kyngdom of heuen to be opened vnto you.<note place="margin">Ge. xv iii. Ro. iiii.</note> The Lorde made a couenaunt with Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that his ſeede ſhulde poſſeſſe a temporall kyngdome and regyment. Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre what a kyngdome it is that is promyſed vnto you, it is not a kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome that floweth with mylke and hony as theyrs dyd.<note place="margin">Exo. ii <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xo. xiii</note> It is a celeſtyal
<pb facs="tcp:5745:16"/> kyngdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> floweth w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grate &amp; <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of god. The confort, ioy, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modyte, wherof no tonge can expreſſe, neither herte can thynke. It is not a kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhal haue an ende, or where y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>habitours may be diſtroyed as they were by nabuchodonoſor,<note place="margin">iiii. Re. x<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>v.</note> it is a king<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhal contynewe for euer. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> celeſtyal cytezens ſhal lyue in ſuche reſt, that nothyng ſhall haue power to inquiet them. I merualye that ye are ſo vnthankful for this bleſſyng. Remembre ye not frome what bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage ye are delyuered? Why haſt ye no better to repayre agayne the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Lorde, which oure enne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes of Babylon ſought for to dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroye. And through theyr fayned ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lynes begyled the rulers of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world, cauſynge them to commyt ydolatry, and to buylde vp hye houſes for to honour &amp; worſhyp theyr Idols in. I do not ſo moche couet &amp; deſyre the ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cellent knowledge of lernyng &amp; elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence
<pb facs="tcp:5745:16"/> whiche y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> famous doctours, oratours, &amp; poetes haue had) wryti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g not onely in the latyn tonge, but alſo in our awne vulgar ſpeche, wherby I mought excyte you to take pleſure i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> redyng of this worke, as I erneſtly deſyre to moue you to take conforte and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſolacyon in redyng &amp; heryng of the worde of god, wherby ye mou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght perceyue and perfytely vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his lyuyng temple (whiche is euen your ſelues) hath ben longe tyme in decay, &amp; now of his mercyful goodnes (w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out our awn deſeruyng) brought agayn to his firſt fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, wherupo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we haue fre liberte to bild. Is it not a ſhame &amp; great rebuke to vs y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we (which haue receiued y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of chriſt, to be called criſtiens) ſhulde appere to be leſſe thankful, &amp; to take any leſſe ioy &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort in repayryng of our te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple, then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes had (whiche lyued onely vnder Moſyes lawe, to bylde agayn their te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of ſtone. whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> peple were delyuered fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyuyte,
<pb facs="tcp:5745:17"/> which Nabuchodonoſor had led vnto Babylon, It was he that mought put to his handes for the buyldyng of the temple agayne. And when the buylders were layenge the foundacyon therof, the people gaue thankes and prayſes vnto the lorde, And lauded hym with Symballes &amp; trompettes.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>d. iii.</note> And many of the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyent fathers &amp; preeſtes whiche had ſene the houſe in his foundacyon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, wepte and cryed for Ioy ſo that the noyes gaue a great ſounde.</p>
            <p>¶This temple was but a temple of ſtone made by mennes handes to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> honoure of god. And where the arke of promyſe and couenaunt that the Lorde made with their fathers was put in, yet note howe they reioyced to ſe it ſet vp agayne. Nowe ye that be of Chryſt,<note place="margin">ii. co. vi.</note> ye are as ſaynt Paule ſayth the temple of god. Why reioyce ye not in the repayryng of your tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple agayne, ye haue a ſure &amp; ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyall
<pb facs="tcp:5745:17"/> foundacyon to buylde vpon, whiche is layde alredy vnto youre handes.<note place="margin">i. Cor. ii<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Chryſt hym ſelfe is youre foundacyon, and though your ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaryes haue attempted to plucke downe ſome ſmall ſtones therof. yet is ther a corner ſtone,<note place="margin">mat. exi. i. Eph. ii</note> which ioyneth the walles togyther, agaynſt whom they had no power.<note place="margin">i. Pe. ii.</note> It is a ſto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>blyng ſtone for all them y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtryue agaynſt it. They haue ſtryued ſo long agaynſt this ſtone that they haue hurte them ſelues. your foundacyon and corner ſtone is bothe one thyng. It is chriſt which wolde haue his temple reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to his preſtyne dignite. And now through his mercyful goodnes hath euery man fre lybertye to put ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto his helpyng hande, accordyng to the gyfte and knowledge that is gyuen hym. But there hath ben a frowarde and crafty ſorte of people that haue hyndered the buyldyng of the lordes temple a great whyle, as
<pb facs="tcp:5745:18"/> ther were ſome that hyndered y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> buyl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyng of the Cyte and te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem Ther were a certayn of the he<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>then people whiche wrote theyr let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters vnto the kyng of perſia (named artaxerſes) whiche ar that tyme had the Empyre in his dominion,<note place="margin">i. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d. iiii.</note> ſayeng yf this Cytye be buylded, and the walles made vp agayne. Then ſhall not they gyue trybute, toll, and yere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly coſtome. And it ſhal apere in Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nycles that this Cytye is ſedycyous and noyſome vnto kynges &amp; regyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they cauſed other alſo to rebel of old, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theſe &amp; ſuche other thynges they mouyd the kyng to ſende his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dement that the worke ſhuld go no further forth, and then ſeaced the worke of the houſe of god at Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lem, and contynued ſo vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .ii. yere of Darius kyng of perſia. And hathe not likewyſe the byſſhops of Rome &amp; theyr adherentes (long tyme fearing the decaye of theyr kyngedome) per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwadyd
<pb facs="tcp:5745:18"/> kynges and prynces, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue that ſuche a lyke matter ſhulde happen vnto them, and that it ſhuld be a cauſe of ſedycyon, yf the temple of god ſhulde be renued and exalted agayne whiche is, yf that the people ſhuld haue the worde of god in theyr maternall tonge, they ſayde it is to hye a matter for them to medle with all, they muſte receaue it at our han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des. And as we do expounde it vnto them. For well they knewe yf that matter came to paſſe, that then theyr crafte and falſehode wolde be ſpyed, they knewe that many of theyr con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitucions and the true worde of god coulde not agre in one mynd togy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. And nowe when ſome of our holy prelates perceyued, that God wolde no longer ſuffre his Goſpell to gyue place to theyr wycked pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes, but that it ſhulde come forthe in ſpyte of theyr beardes. Then beganne they to cloke the matter
<pb facs="tcp:5745:19"/> and as though they were innocent of all maner of harmes, when they ſawe no remedy ſayd, they were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented that it ſhulde come forthe in Englyſſhe, ſo that it mought be tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tranſlated. They put great dow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes in the true tranſlacyon therof. But howe many of them dyd there put to theyr helpyng handes for the tranſlatyng of it. I thynke verely yf other men had not taken more payn therin then they dyd, it wold not yet haue come to that poynt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is nowe come vnto. And how they wreſted &amp; peruerted the ſcryptures when they had them in theyr awne handes, and that all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were forbydden to medle therwith but them ſelues. It is euy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent ynough to euery man that hath ony zele vnto the trueth. He is very ſymply lerned that doth not ꝑceyue how wrongfully they haue applyed this ſayeng of Chriſte to Peter. Tu es Petrꝰ et dabo tibi claues.<note place="margin">mat. xvi luce. vii.</note> &amp;c. And
<pb facs="tcp:5745:19"/> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lepers that were clenſed whome Chriſt bad to go and ſhew the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues to the preeſtes,<note place="margin">leui. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> whiche that famous clerke and doctour Eraſmus in his paraphraſes vpon the goſpell dothe otherwyſe expounde it, than I haue herde dyuers bothe preeſtes &amp; freres whiche with that texte wolde bolſter vp theyr auriculer confeſſyon. And an hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred ſuche places wreſted they in ſcrypture, to make for theyr pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. I wyll not moche treate of that matter, for ſuche as be well lerned, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> god hath rayſed vp to ſet forth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> trueth of his glory &amp; to repayre agay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne, his te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple haue both wrytten &amp; ſpo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken of theyr falſe peruertyng of the ſcryptures moche better then I can do. But truely I thynke in my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience that they ſhal rendre a ſtrayte rekenyng for the people of god who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they haue dyſceyued with the ſcryp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures ſo vntruely applyed &amp; taught vnto them, I pray god to graunt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:5745:20"/> his mercye, for the thynge is not ſo lyght as euery man thynkes it to be<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> It dothe appere in the fyrſt boke of Eſdras,<note place="margin">i. Eſd. i</note> after that god had ſtyred vp the ſpyryte of Cyrus kynge of perſia to haue the houſe of god buylded a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayn at Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Iuda, and that he had gyuen fre lyberty to all them that were of his people,<note place="margin">ii. Para. xxxvi.</note> and had byn captyue long tyme in babylon to go home into theyr owne lande agayne to buylde the houſe of the lorde, ther were a certayne of the hethen people as ye haue red before that letted the goynge forthe of the worke after it was begon, ſo that it ſtode in a ſtay, vntyll kynge Daryus tyme whiche afterward reygned ouer the perſia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. Thys Darius founde out in the ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brary houſe of kyng Cyrus his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyceſſour that he had gyuen in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement to buylde the houſe of the lord at Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>. vi.</note> Wherfore he mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uyd w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame zele &amp; mynde reneweth
<pb facs="tcp:5745:20"/> the comaundement of Cirus, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ueth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lycence to buyld y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> temple w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all thynges neceſſary ther vnto be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longynge. Who wyl not thynke but that this was an exydynge conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon and com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orte to all the people, whiche couetyd the goynge forth of the lordes worke, and a great dyſco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort vnto all them, that deſyred the hynderaunce of the ſame. And as it is to be thought of them, ſo is it lyke<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wyſe to be ſuppoſed of vs in this pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſent tyme. Almyghty god the father hath moued the herte of our mooſt gracyous kyng to loke in the library In the holy wyll and teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of his ſon Ieſus chriſt our only ſauiour, be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yng the fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dacion of his te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which Peter Paule, Iames,<note place="margin">i. Cor. iii</note> Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apoſtles w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> diuers other holy me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bylded, &amp; receiued a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord to bild vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> none other fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which he had laid. Bbut the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e ther ſuch a ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t as I haue wrytte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:5745:21"/> enuyed the goyng forthe of the lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des worke. And though it were out of their powers to diſtroy it, yet haue they hyndred the ſame a long ſeaſon. But as the wyll of god is (with who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there is no reaſon to be made, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he dothe it more now then at an other tyme) our godly kyng beynge inſpired with the ſpirite of grace, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nueth the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundemente of our ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uyour Chriſt, geuyng fre lybertye to buylde vp y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lordes temples agayne. He feareth not the aduerſaryes ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, but expulſeth them, and wypeth awaye Idolatry.<note place="margin">iiii. Reg xviii. Num. xxi</note> Euen as the good kynge Eſechias dyd, whiche brake downe the braſen ſerpent y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Moyſes had made for a remembraunce of the power and goodneſſe of god, yet for co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myttyng Idolatry and worſhyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge of it he feared not to breake it downe, neyther theyr hye houſes in whom they worſhypped their ydols. And lyke vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good kyng Ioſias,<note place="margin">iiii. Reg xxii.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:5745:21"/> when the boke of the law was found in the houſe of the lorde, after he had mourned becauſe his Fathers had not herkened vnto that boke to do al that was wrytten therin. He cauſed it to be red vnto all his people, and made a couenaunt with them, that they ſhulde walke after the lord, and kepe his commaundementes, wyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes and ordynau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, with al theyr herte, and with all theyr ſoule.<note place="margin">iiii. Reg xxiii.</note> And that they ſhulde ſet vp the wordes of the couenaunt whiche were wrytten in that boke. And all the people en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred in to the couenaunt. And hathe not our moſt godly kyng done euen in lyke maner. Hath he not ſent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brode through all his realme, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> couenaunt of the Lorde (whiche is his holy goſpel) ſhulde be truely and and ſyncerly preached vnto all his people. And becauſe they ſhulde the better obſerue and kepe the Lordes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementes and walke in his
<pb facs="tcp:5745:22"/> his wayis hath he not gyuen his pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple fre lybertye to haue the lawe of the lorde in theyr maternall tonge? who wyll thynke thys to be a ſmale benefyte? truely in my opynyon it is of ſuche valure that Englyſhe men had neuer greater cauſe to thanke god for and to praye for the gracy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous proſperytye of theyr kynge then for this matter, it is a thyng hyely to be extemed for a kynge to haue Iuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyce mynyſtred w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in his realme, that as the ſayenge is. The Lambe maye dwel by the Wolfe, the pore man by the rycher and one quyetly to lyue by another. It is a thynge of great co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort vnto that realme, which hath a wyſe poletyke &amp; valyaunt prynce to defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d his domynyon agaynſt forren nacyons, &amp; rebellyons yf nede do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quyre, it is a greate benefyte of god vnto that countrey that hath a kynd louynge and mercyfull prynce vnto his people. Now yf theſe thynges w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:5745:22"/> many mo then I can recyte be occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyons, vnto ſubiectes to beare fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full hertes and true obedyence vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to theyr ſouerayne lorde and kynge. As I ſayde before Englyſſhe men were neuer more bounde to it then they be nowe. But yet amonge all thynges yf I could recyte a thouſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d more then I can do, yet coulde I not reken one thynge wherin we ought to receyue ſo great conſolacyon. And hertely to reioyſe in / as in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> god hath ſent vs a kynge which ſo gracyouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye ſettyth forthe his glory &amp; cauſeth his people to be fed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ghoſtly fode whiche chriſt ſpake of.<note place="margin">Mat. iiii Deu viii ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>. x<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i.</note> Man lyueth not only by brede, but by euery word that procedyth out of the mouthe of god. The holy Goſpels are the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des that procedith out of his mouth.</p>
            <p>¶And yf the people had bene ſo long kepte frome bodelye ſuſtyna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unce as they haue bene frome theyr ghoſtlye foode.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:5745:23"/>
            <p>I thynke there wold haue ben but a ſlender company remaynyng at this tyme to inhabyte this lande. And yet it is a ſtraunge rekenyng to here the vnwyſe ſayenges of many of the peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple, ſay they not, why ſhulde we not lyue as our fathers hath done before vs, they beleued this, and they bele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued that. And we thynke there were as good men in thoſe dayes as there be nowe. And why ſhulde we not do as they dyd. This is their opinions, wherunto me thynke I coulde make them a reaſonable anſwere (yf reaſon wolde ſuffyſe to ſatyſfy them.) This is true y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the worde of god was kepte from our fathers, &amp; they were made to beleue that yf they ſhulde exercyſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues therin it wolde make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heretykes. And in ſtede therof they were fed with the byſſhop of Romes conſtytucyons, ſo that in contynu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunce the lyuely fayth that was due vnto the worde of god was chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged
<pb facs="tcp:5745:23"/> and gyue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto deed Ceremonyes. I pray you take me not now at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyrſt, that by this ſayeng I entende to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alowe all good Ceremonyes. Do not as the ſayeng is of the nunne, when ſhe had red (Omnia probate) becauſe it ſerued her intente red no ferther, where the nexte wordes folowynge were (quod bonum eſt tenete.) Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye haue ſene my worke thorowly ye ſhall perceyue what my conſcyence doth alowe and dyſalowe. But to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tourne to my matter. I ſayd it was gyuen vnto Ceremonyes that which apperteyned vnto the worde of god. And the worde of god was kepte fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our fathers, whiche is now declared vnto vs, they coulde not here it for it was not taught vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, they could not ſe it for it was kepte from them. Wherfore ſeyng we here that which they herd not, ſe that they ſawe not, &amp; know that they knew not, merueyll not though we do the thinges which
<pb facs="tcp:5745:24"/> they dyd not, there were moche more foly to be imputed vnto vs for fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowynge of theyr wayes. Then vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to one that wolde take on hym to ryde a farre iourney by nyght which knewe neuer a fote of his way. And were alſo certayne that no man wold tel hym the ſtreyght way. The lyght is gyuen vnto vs, what madneſſe were it to walke then in darkeneſſe. The redye waye that we ought to walke in is manyfeſted vnto vs. Is it not then of a frowarde mynde that many do refuſe it. Perchaunce there be dyuers that ſtande in dowte whether the wayes that theyr Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers walked were perfyte, eyther els the wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es that men are nowe taught to walke in. To them that be of that mynde I ſaye, yf there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne any wrytynges what faythe youre Fathers were of. And what wayes they walked then compare
<pb facs="tcp:5745:24"/> them to the ſcrypture and wyll of God, And yf they agre therwithall, dowte ye not but they be good, and yf not then thynke not the contrary but they be euyll. For it is the true twytche ſtone to trye out the good frome the bad. And truely yf ye wyll folowe them whoſe wayes and doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trynes agreed not with the ſcripture of God / bycauſe they had it not / nor coulde not be ſuffered to haue it. And ye haue it dayly preached vnto you, and maye rede it and here it in your mother tonge yf you lyſte, I can not le the contrarye, but where as they offended of ygnorancy, your offence is of obſtynacye. And ye may be counted madder then they whiche wyll wyllyngely ronne into the fyre and burne them ſelues. ¶For when the booke of the lawe of God, was founde in the Temple, whiche had not bene ſene longe tyme before
<pb facs="tcp:5745:25"/> and brought to Ioſyas the kyng,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ii. Reg xxii.</note> he wepte and rent his clothes fearynge leeſt the wrathe of god ſhulde come vpon hym &amp; his people, becauſe their fathers had not herkened vnto the wordes of that boke, to do all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was wrytten vnto them therin. He mour<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned for his fathers iniquites &amp; ſayd not as men ſaye nowe adayes. Why ſhulde we not lyue as our Fathers haue lyued, or why ſhulde we not do as our fathers haue done before vs, for yf our fathers had ſene the dayes that we ſe, many of them wolde haue reioyſed therof moche more then we do. And I thynke not the contrary but they dyd alſo couete &amp; deſyre w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all theyr hertes &amp; were full ſory that they coulde not ſe it. Wherfore I myſtruſt no more the mercy of God to be vpon them, then it was vpon dyuers holy men that were in this worlde before Chryſt came to ſuffre his paſſyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which faythfully beleued
<pb facs="tcp:5745:25"/> in his comyng to redeme the worlde for ſynne,<note place="margin">Luce. x<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and many coueted to ſe the dayes of the lorde, whiche ſawe it not (but in faythe) Symeon deſyred de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyred it and opteyned his deſyre. And when he had ſene Chriſt, beyng but a chylde and he an olde ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">Luc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> his ſayeng was (Nunc dimittis ſeruum tuum domine. &amp;c.) Nowe lorde ſuffre thou thy ſeruaunte to departe in peace, for myne eyes haue ſene thy ſauyour wherfore all ye in whom there is any ſparke of fayth to be redemed by the merytes of Chriſt. By the which the holy fathers that were here before Chriſt came, and haue ben ſyns that tyme, &amp; euer ſhall be vnto the worl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des ende are ſaued. I exhorte and de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyre to receyue this holy doctryne y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is now offred vnto you. And not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtynatly to refuſe it. For there is mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che more to be requyred at your han<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des then at your fathers, which had not that lyght opened and lyghted
<pb facs="tcp:5745:26"/> vnto them that you haue. And as I hope to be ſauyd my ſelfe, ſo do I couyt the ſaluacyon of your ſoules. Wherfore I inſtantly deſyre you to haue a perfyte fayth in Ieſus chriſt. ſo that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> workes therof may teſtefye your fayth to be good, euen as good fruyt doth teſtefy the tre to be good. But beware that in no condycyon ye attrybute onye ſaluacyon to be due vnto your dedes but vnto fayth on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. For when ye haue done all that euer ye can do, yet ſay ye be vnprofy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>table ſeruauntes. And yet yf ye do not good workes your faythe is but a ded fayth, &amp; no more extemed to be good,<note place="margin">Luce. vi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t, vii</note> then a tre is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bryngeth forthe euyl fruyt, for it is the good tre that cauſeth the fruit to be good, and not the fruyt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> maketh the tre good, ſo lykewyſe it is fayth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> bringeth forth good workes, &amp; not workes good faith. I had not thought to haue ſpo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo moche of faith &amp; workes, had I
<pb facs="tcp:5745:26"/> not herde w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> myne eares notw<hi rend="sup">t</hi>ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſcrypture is in Englyſſhe &amp; that it is preached vnto them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny men yet can not frame theyr fayth in the merytes of Chryſt to be onely a ſuffycyent ſaluacyon for them, but wolde patche it vp w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their awne me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rytes. Where as concernyng y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, they are greatly diſceyued, for good wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes is but a teſtymony that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faythe is good, by the whiche onely all our ſaluacyon cometh. And yet is there an other thyng wherwith y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chryſten co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregacyon haue ben pyteouſly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued, beſyde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> confydence in their awne good workes in truſtyng to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> merites of ſayntes euery man as his affeccyon lay, ſome vnto one ſaynt &amp; ſome vnto an other, &amp; yet y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayntes merytes were inſufficient to ſaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues, for al they wer ſaued by chriſt as we are bound to truſt for to be. And thoughe ſome wolde obiecte a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt me, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they put no confydence in the ſayntes merytes, but onely
<pb facs="tcp:5745:27"/> in the ſayntes merytes, but onely prayed the ſayntes to pray for them. I meruayle the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wherof it came that men had more affeccyon to one ſaynt then to another, in one place then in an other. This ye can not deny me, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thyng is to apparent. Thoughe ye deny me the fyrſt whiche is as trewe as that. What is he that hathe bene one of theſe pope holy pylgrymes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> can excuſe hym ſelfe for puttyng dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſyte not onely betwyxte ſaynt and ſaynt, but alſo betwyxte ymage and ymage. Who thought that ſaynt Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes was ſo good in any place as at Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poſtella, or ſaynt Peter at Rome. And here within this realme did ony of the holy pylgrymes thynke oure lady of Ipſwytch, Worceſtre, Wylſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, or any of them all to be ſo boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tefull as our lady of Walſyngham. No our lady of Penryce in Wales was not lyke vnto her. was not this a goodly honour gyuen to our Lady
<pb facs="tcp:5745:27"/> &amp; to the ſayntes, to thynke the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be more hooly in one place then in an other, or that any holyneſſe, grace or vertue at all ſhulde perſyſt in a payn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted ſtocke or ſtone cloke the matter who that lyſt. And ye that thynke to be wyſe with the beſt that can make for your excuſe. An ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred thouſand poore people within this realme yet lyuyng haue ben and be diſceyued w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſuche affeccyonate and peuyſſhe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynes. And I am ſure that god ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as wel for them as for thoſe that were theyr furred hodes, and beleue verely that they haue bene ceduced therunto by ſuche as nowe wynke at the matter, which were not aſhamed to bely the ſayntes and to mocke the people with theyr fayned myracles. I thynke there can be no greater diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>honoure done vnto the ſayntes then with ſuche vyce and vnthryftyneſſe, as in dyuers places folowed of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented worſhypyng of them. There
<pb facs="tcp:5745:28"/> is a cuſtome vſed ſpecyally in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> weſt parte of England to haue watches kept at churches &amp; chapels vpon the ſaintes eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. And if eating, drinking kiſſyng, pipyng, ſyngyng, &amp; dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſyng be a mete thyng to honour y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaynt &amp; to be vſed in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> temple, then is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaynt as wel honoured &amp; the church as wel vſed as can be thought or deuyſed. They haue a terme theris called bou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtenyng, which is to make the blynd to ſe, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dombe to ſpeke, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> defe to here, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> halt &amp; lame to go. True it is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they which neuer ſaw nor had hering nor felte any thyng at all haue opteyned this grace there (but not i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>medyatly) for it was euer .xl. wekes aft. Before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> benefite of this bouſteni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g toke his ꝑfeccyon ye know what I meane. if I ſhuld recyte y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> abhomynacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s (which I aſhame to put i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> writyng or remem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce) it wold co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teyne a large volu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me of it ſelf.<note place="margin">mat. xxi Re. viii Eſa. v. Ier. vii</note> Chriſt draue out y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> byers &amp; ſellers of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple ſayng my houſe is a hous of prayer, which ye haue made
<pb facs="tcp:5745:28"/> a den of theues, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>th be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerted to a very good vſe, for vnder a <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>tence of prayer aperyng to folow y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wyl of chriſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſtes haue ꝑ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mytted his houſe to be chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a den of theues to a den of rybaldes &amp; harlottes. And though they wold ſay y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no acte of ſyn was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mytted in the church, yet true it is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> occaſyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſyn aroſe oftymes onely of theyr metyng ther, &amp; the bargens of vyce was ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> made &amp; apoynted there, &amp; the thyng which elswher could not be brought to paſſe at their comyng to ſuch holy places toke effect there as it ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ape<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yere came about. O mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciful god y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pictures of his ſayntes ſhuld not only be ſet vp to cauſe his people to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit ydolatry, but for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uetouſnes of their offring pence ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred to be a cloke of vice, ſyn &amp; ribau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dry, but what meruayl is it that they haue ſo abuſed the pyctures of his ſayntes which feare not to abuſe the pycture of hym ſelfe &amp; his precyous
<pb facs="tcp:5745:29"/> blood ſo belyeng it that it may cauſe any chryſten herte to lament &amp; wepe to thynke theron, &amp; though y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thyng haue ben wrytten and preached of al redy, yet can it not be to often put in remembraunce to cauſe both the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and permytters therof to repent and be aſhamed of theyr foly, yf ther be any grace in them. I omyt many thynges to wryte of becauſe that all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can not yet abide to here y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth. But I truſt the tyme is come that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truthe ſhal declare it ſelfe as concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayntes, I wolde men ſhulde iudge none otherwiſe of me, but that I loue them as well and better then they whiche lycke &amp; kyſſe theyr yma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. For I wolde that all honoure y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is due vnto them ſhulde be gyuen them. But in no condycyon that any thyng whiche dothe apperteyne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chryſt ſhulde be taken from hym. For it doth appere by the great pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye haue take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſeke theſe holy
<pb facs="tcp:5745:29"/> places, weryeng of your bodyes, ſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyng of your ſubſtaunce, &amp; many le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng theyr chyldren and houſholde at home in penury, and by knelynge, kyſſyng &amp; praye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ymages, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye haue a certayne fayth &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fydence in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wherin ye rob god of his due honour and glory, but there be a ſort of crafty ſcole mayſters whiche haue taught you to ſaye, when any ſuche thynges is imputed vnto you that it is all for goddes ſake y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye do it, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye do it for to pleaſe god withall. Alas that ye wyl ſtyl be ſo dyſceyued to ſuppoſe that ye pleaſe hym, with that thyng whiche hyghly dothe dyſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pleaſe hym. Why wyll ye not loke in his teſtament, or herke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers that ye maye knowe what his godly wyll is,<note place="margin">rom. iii. Ephe. v teſſ. iiii.</note> &amp; what ye ſhulde do to pleaſe hym. And yf ye thynke ye are not bounde to knowe his wyll, but to folow your awne wylles, &amp; fantaſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tycall appetytes, &amp; the wylles of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:5745:30"/> whiche ſought not the glory of God, but their awne fylthy lucre &amp; aduau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tage. Then doth the lawe of god no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng at all aperteyne vnto you. It is to be thought y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye haue a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne zele vnto Chriſt, but it is not accordyng to truthe. Wherfore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware that zele wyll diſceyue you, for as it ſhal be no good ple for a man y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hath commytted felony, murdre, or otherwyſe tranſgreſſed the kynges lawes, to ſay that he knew them not. No more it ſhall be for you y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> offende the lawes and wyll of God to make ſuche a lyke anſwere, ſpecyally to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whiche maye knowe it yf they lyſt. There be certeyne perſones whiche ſay it is better not to know y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawes of God then to knowe them and fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe them not. In dede to ſome men I thynke it is better but not vnto all men. It is better to oure Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers whiche coulde not be ſuffered to knowe it, then vnto ſuche as at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme attayned the knowledge therof
<pb facs="tcp:5745:30"/> and folowed it not.<note place="margin">Luce. xii</note> For Chriſt ſayth to whom moche is gyuen, there is moche to be requyred of hym. But nowe at this tyme, the goſpell &amp; wyll of god is offered vnto all men. It is preached &amp; taught vnto them, who ſo euer do refuſe to receyue and here it. There is as moch or more to be layd vnto his charge, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which knoweth it and foloweth it not, there is no excuſe to be made in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. why do they refuſe it but becauſe they wolde not folowe it. And there be ſome y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> haue an other reaſon. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde ſay they theſe newe goſpellers how vnthryftely many of them lyue, who are more couetous then they be, where regneth enuy, rancour, &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyce more then in their hertes. They ſpeke of loue, concorde and charyte, yet no men ſhowe leſſe charyte, nor leſſe loue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they do, they be proude, they be lecherus, &amp; al i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vices as euyl or wors the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they which haue not the
<pb facs="tcp:5745:31"/> goſpell. Truely I ſay euery man is bound to know it &amp; folowe the ſame to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vttereſt of his power, and they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be ſuche as ye haue herde reported of, reken them to be ſclaunderers of the worde of god in theyr dedes as other men are in wordes, that ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke euyll of it.<note place="margin">Luce. xii Iac. iiii</note> And theyr knoweledge ſhalbe euyll vnto them. For the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunte that knewe his lordes wyll, and dyd it not, ſhalbe beaten with many ſtrypes. Let not the noughty conuerſacyon of the euyl, plucke bac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke your hertes from the knoweledge of gods word, for it is not the ſcryp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture that maketh them euyll.<note place="margin">Pſal. xxxvi.</note> But it byddethe them to abſtayne frome euyll and do good, and ſuche as be euyl knowyng goddes worde, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oute fayle wolde be wars yf they knewe it not. But throughe theyr noughty lyuyng they cauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worde of god to be euyll ſpoken of, ſo that they offende not onelye them ſelues,
<pb facs="tcp:5745:31"/> but are an occaſyon to other men to offende alſo, therfore the more ſynne is in them. Beware howe ye ſpeake euyll of the worde of god, for it is a ſynne greater then al your good wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes can ſatyſfye agayne for it. Thyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke not, nor ſaye not, bycauſe ſuche men, and ſuche men be nothynge the better for the Goſpell. Therfore I wyll not medle with it. What canſt thou tell what god wolde worke in thy herte yf thou dydeſt rede it, the thyng is ſo good of it ſelfe, that thou art far from grace to thinke it wold worke any euyll in the. Doyſt thou thinke becauſe thou ſeeſt ſome lewde perſons that knowe it &amp; abuſe theyr knowlege that thou ſhuldeſt do lyke wyſe. O folyſſhe man that ſo doeſt myſtruſt the mercye and goodneſſe of God towardes the, His good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and mercye is layde forth for al men and though euery man haue not grace to attayne vnto it. yet dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers
<pb facs="tcp:5745:32"/> men whiche haue it not at one tyme maye haue it at an other. And ſo they whome thou ſeyſt to be euyll and knowe the ſcrypture yet beware diſpyſe not nor reſuſe not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcripture therfore for it may worke in their her<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes at ſome other tyme when it ſhall pleaſe god, to whom y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> mayſt apoynt no tyme. Ther is yet an other opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſayeng they wyl here no prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chyng, becauſe the preachers agre no better. Truely it is an vnwyſe rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and in my mynde but a fayned excuſe, for yf all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> clergy of England agreed in one and preached one true way and doctryne yet many, I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe wolde be no more dylygent in heryng but as ſlowe to come to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons as they be now, for thankes be to god y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thing is merely wel brought to paſſe, there are very fewe ſermons made (ſpecyally in the Cyte and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boute the Cyte of London) whiche is in the herte of the realme, that the
<pb facs="tcp:5745:32"/> one is repugnaunt vnto the other. Perchaunce there be ſome curres y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wolde fayne barke were it not that they more feared y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> temporal ſcourge then the ſworde and punyſſhment of God. And what be theſe that ſay they wyll here no preachynge, but euen they whiche alſo wyll not rede the ſcrypture neyther here it redde vnto them, wherfore they are to be repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of frowarde and obſtynat ygno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rancy. Who is ſo blynde as they that wyll not ſe. And who are more deffer then they that wyll not here. For tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of this effycacy is the word of god that who ſoeuer wyll come to rede it, or to the preachynge therof, with a pure true and vnfayned mynde, wyl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lynge to learne, and not to be a bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bler, and a buſy dyſputer thereof. He ſhall not all onely receyue great conforte and conſolacyon therein. But alſo the very fruyte and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge to deſerne the trewe preacher
<pb facs="tcp:5745:33"/> of god, from hym y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> falſly peruerteth the ſcryptures to mayntayne ther with hys awne wycked intent and purpoſe. Nowe ſeyng that the word of god is ſo excellent a thynge that no condygne prayſe maye be gyuen therunto. Wo maye they be that are ſclaunderers therof.<note place="margin">zacha.</note> Wherfore returne with a contryte mynde vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to god that he may turne vnto you, truſt vnto his promys and he wyll not dyſceaue you. And ſaye not with your ſelues, I am old, I haue lyued this many yeres after this forte, It is to late for me to chaunge nowe. Remembre the parable of certayne men that were hyred to worke in the houſholders vyneyarde,<note place="margin">M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> ſome came in the mornyng, ſome at noone, and ſome in the euenynge, and they that came laſt had lyke rewarde w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> them that came fyrſt, &amp; they whiche came fyrſt, and at none, grudged at them that came laſte, bycauſe they had
<pb facs="tcp:5745:33"/> lyke rewarde with them. Then ſayd the lord of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vyneyarde, why grudge ye, haue I not gyuen you your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſe, why ſhuld I not gyue to euery man as it pleaſeth me. So men are called to repentau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, ſome in youthe ſome in mydle age, and ſome in olde age. And the lorde may rewarde hym as well that came laſt as he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> came fyrſt, and no man may ſay vnto hym why do you ſo. So it appereth that heuen is not due vnto mennes good workes and dedes, but it is gyuen of the fre lyberte and goodneſſe of God vnto al them that truſteth in his pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>myſe, hauyng a perfyte fayth in Ieſꝰ Chriſt. And howe that fayth may be knowen, I haue wrytten you before. And yf ye meruayll why the preeſtes in tyme paſt tolde you not this tale, and what y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cauſe was that they for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bade you the ſcrypture. Truely they knew wel that theyr lyuyng dyd not accorde therwithall, and that it was
<pb facs="tcp:5745:34"/> the thyng that wolde manyfeſt their pryde, theyr couetouſneſſe, and all theyr ſynfull lyuyng. Wherfore they bare men in hand that it was to hye matters for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to meddle with, but that they muſt receaue it of them. And how truly they gaue it vnto the peple. He y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hath eares to here let him heare, and he that hath eies to ſe let him ſe.<note place="margin">Luc. x.</note> Beholde for the kyngedome of god is come nye vnto you, whiche ye deſire daylt in your Pater noſter, when ye ſaye (adueniat regnum tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um) the Goſpel is preached and laid before you, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye may therin ſeke oute what his wyl is,<note place="margin">Luce. xi Mat. vii</note> he byddes you ſeke and ye ſhal fynd, knocke and it ſhal be opened vnto you, where wyll ye ſeke but in his holy teſtament. Wyll ye ſeke it in the byſſhops of romes decretals and in Legenda aurea as your fathers dyd, truly ye may knoc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke then vntyll your heades ake and ſeke vntyll your eies be blynde, and
<pb facs="tcp:5745:34"/> yet not fynde the way to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kyngdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e of god, ye ſhall as ſone fynd it in Be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uys of Hampto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; Guy of warwycke as amonge the holy bokes that ye &amp; your fathers in tyme paſt haue ben permytted to loke on, but ſhulde I ſaye that all oure fathers are loſſe whiche were not taught nor coulde not be ſuffered to knowe the perfyte waye god forbyde, for when Chryſte ſayd to his diſciples.<note place="margin">Math. xix. mar. x.</note> It is as harde for a Camell to go throughe the eye of a nedle as for a ryche man to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre into the kyngedome of heauen they aunſweryd Lorde who then ſhal be ſauyd? He ſayd that which is impoſſyble vnto men is poſſyble ynough vnto god now ſeynge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng is impoſſyble vnto God.<note place="margin">Luce. xiii.</note> I dout not but manye of oure fathers which walked not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtreight path vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to chriſt, becauſe they could not be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ferid to know it (yet hauing a zele &amp; loui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g mi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vnto hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> optained his mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cye
<pb facs="tcp:5745:35"/> But vnto vs whiche haue the open way declared frowardly to refuſe it there is non excuſe wyll ſerue.</p>
            <p>¶And nowe to retourne agayne to a parte of my purpoſe, I erneſtly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horte all you whiche are not alonely my natyue countrey men, but alſo re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>demed with the ſame precyous blood that I am,<note place="margin">Rom. v. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>. ix. i Pet. i i Ioh. i.</note> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye wyll put away your co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fydence in pilgrymages vnto deed ſayntes and ymages. And to thynke as the truthe is, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it was but a thyng inuented to rob from you your tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall ſubſtaunce, which the inſacya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble bely beaſtes dyd ſo moche couet and deſyre, that they nothyng regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, what became of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> precious ſoule of man, which golde nor ſyluer, man nor woman, ſaynt nor aungel coulde redeme, but onely Ieſus Chriſte, the immaculate lambe, whiche was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelated vnto ſaynt Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">Apo. v.</note> that was founde worthy to open the boke with the .vii. ſeales and none but he nor to
<pb facs="tcp:5745:35"/> loke theron, in heuen in erthe nor vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> erthe. Thynke ye yf any thyng coulde haue redemed mannes ſoule, but onely the ſonne of God, that he ſhulde haue ben ſent in to this world to ſuffre hungre, colde, anguyſſhe, payn and cruel deth, no ſurely. Why are ye not the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aſhamed to ſeke vnto any other but vnto hym. Why ronne you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o this ymage &amp; that ymage, and put dyfference among the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and theyr holy places as though one were bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then an other, where there is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer a good as ye do vſe them. And to thynke that ye pleaſe god and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour hym in ſekyng of ſuche places. I ſay playnly yo dyſpleaſe hym, for ye do contrary to his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dement, wherin ye dyſhonour hym as moche as may be. The workes that ought to be done pleaſyng and acceptable in the ſyght of god are conteyned in the holy ſcryptures,<note place="margin">Deu. v</note> by the whiche ye are playnly prohibited both to make
<pb facs="tcp:5745:36"/> any ymage, &amp; to worſhyp them. And what greater worſhyp can ye do vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to knele vnto them kyſſe them, ſet vp candels before them, &amp; offre your mony vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. I thynke I mought alſo ſay (and lye not) pray vnto them. For wherof ſhulde this inanne and vayne ſpeche aryſe with out a ſertayne truſt in them. When the people wold ſaye, our vleſſyd la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Walſyngha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> helpe me, the holy rode of North dore, and the croſſe of Chaldon be my comforte, the trewe remembraunce of the croſſe of chriſt wherin they ought only to ſeke their conſolacyon, ioy &amp; tonforte, was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten or at leſt abuſed vnto a great nombre of croſſes &amp; rodes within this realme. For the which (as reaſon is) myny are pulled downe, but ther re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne ſome yet, for all thynges can not be done at one tyme. I knewe a holy rode ſtandyng in Englande in a houſe of freres y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which haue made
<pb facs="tcp:5745:36"/> the people to beleue &amp; thynke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the heare of his heed &amp; berde dyd grow. What chryſten herre can ſuffre this iniury &amp; mockyng of the people with the picture of chriſt to be vnrebuked wrytten &amp; ſpoken agaynſt. One of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> freres reported to a frende of myne, that yf it were not for that rode, they wyſt not howe to lyue, were not they worthy to haue a good lyuyng y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked it out w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pycture of chriſt ſo exe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crably vſed. wer not y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> prayers of thes holy men ſuppoſe you of great effect before god. wer not theſe perfyte rely<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gyous me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; all thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges wel beſtowed y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was gyue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Iudge ye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> haue any reaſon or iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, for in my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceyte ye can not diſpleaſe god more then w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> mayntenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of ſuch ydle &amp; abhomynable beggers, &amp; I thynke ther can be no greter diſhonour done vnto god the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> honouring of his pic<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture ſo abuſed, &amp; it is certayn y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mytted ydolatry w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> kneli<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, praye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g &amp; offring to it, &amp; ſei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ye co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit ydolatry
<pb facs="tcp:5745:37"/> in the veneracyon of his awne pyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. It is vndowted playne ydola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try to worſhyp or pray to any pyctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res or ymages of ſayntes, whiche in their lyfe tyme refuſed all honoure refarryng it vnto God, whome they ſought out in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcryptures and prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, taught &amp; exhorted all men vnto hym they ſent them vnto no ſtockes nor ſtones to offre nor to worſhyp them. Nor they requyred no worſhip to be gyuen to them ſelues, nor ſayd not we ſhall ſaue you, but ſent men vnto Chriſt, and ſayd folowe vs vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chryſt. Dyd not ſaynt Paule re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue the people becauſe they conten<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded amonge them ſelues ſayenge I holde of Paule,<note place="margin">1. Cor. i.</note> I holde of Appolo. And at an other tyme whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they wold haue done ſacrifice vnto hym &amp; Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabas.<note place="margin">Act. xiiii</note> Dyd not they rent their clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes, ſayeng why do ye this, we are mortall men as ye be &amp; preache vnto you the goſpell, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye ſhulde tourne
<pb facs="tcp:5745:37"/> from theſe vayne thynges vnto the lyuyng god. They wold y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al honour ſhulde be gyuen to god, &amp; not to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues, &amp; yet yf ſayntes ought to be honoured for their vertuous &amp; holy lyfe. And for conuertynge of the people vnto the true fayth of Chriſt. I am ſure that ſaint Paule deſerued it as well as any of them all. Thomas of Cauntorbury (whiche byed for many proper poyntes, yf all thynges were truely perſpected and loked vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) deſerued not to haue lyke honour vnto hym, whiche I am ſure is to be nombred among the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſayd. (No<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nobis dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nobis,<note place="margin">Pſal. Cxiii.</note> ſed nomini tuo da gloria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) Not vnto vs lord, not vnto vs, but vnto thy name gyue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glory. Nowe ſeyng y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſayntes do refuſe ſuch honour, which cometh of a ſuperſticious holynes, &amp; that their honour &amp; glory perſyſteth onely in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true honourynge of god, me thynke there is more foly in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people (which
<pb facs="tcp:5745:38"/> after ſuche a ſorte wyl honour them) the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ther is to be imputed vnto thoſe whiche ſeke to ſerue ſuche mayſters that wyl non of their ſeruyce, but vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terlye refuſe it. Conſyder who it is which aboue al thynges ought to be honored &amp; ſerued, it is he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wyl refuſe none which faythfully wyl come vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to him, it is he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is of power to kepe all men, &amp; gyueth fode to al lyuynge creatures, it is he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> helpeth all them which cal vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him, purpoſyng to ob<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſerue his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes me thynke this maiſter is mete to be ſerued, but let no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thynke himſelfe mete to do him ſeruyce, whiche whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſeyth or heryth what his mayſters wyl &amp; ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure is to be done, wyl do a thing co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarye to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, as thoughe he were wyſer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his mayſter. I grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ther be fewe or non of his ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes that haue not offendyd him, onleſſe they were preſeruyd by his grace. But he is ſuche a maiſter y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wyl not caſte of
<pb facs="tcp:5745:38"/> his ſeruaunt for euery tryfle &amp; ſclen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre faute, no though he haue hyghly treſpaſed agaynſt hym &amp; tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſgreſſed his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dementes ſo he do not vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly refuſe hym. But when he reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bres his foly, &amp; returnes with a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryte mynde, knowledgyng his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, &amp; requy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yng pardon, he is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes redy to forgyue &amp; to receyue hym agayn,<note place="margin">Luc. xv</note> eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father was y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceyued his ſonne, which had ben in a ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge cuntrey, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſumed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> porcyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his ſubſtance which his father ga<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue hym, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he came home naked he clothed hym &amp; feaſted him w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a fatted calfe, ſayng to his fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, let vs be me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry. Beholde my ſon which was loſt &amp; is fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d agayn. So ye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>tende to be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people of god, reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your myn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des how ye haue beſtowed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> porcyon of your ſubſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, I meane not only of your te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poral ſubſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, but of the true &amp; ꝓfyte fayth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you promyſed at your baptym to bere vnto Ieſꝰ chriſt
<pb facs="tcp:5745:39"/> as concernynge youre tranſſytorye goodes, you can not denye but ye haue beſtowed it on deed Images, wher his wyl is, ye ſhuld relyue ther with his awne quycke and lyuynge Image.<note place="margin">Luce. xxv.</note> The poore people whiche be ſycke, lame and blynd, and the impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and agyd which can not labour and ſuche as be in pryſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. ye haue not folowed his pleaſure, but done con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary vnto it. Wherfore truly ye are not mete ſeruauntes for him, oneles ye repent your folly and folyſſhe yg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noraunce, yf ye allege that your goſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly fathers taught you this to do. I ſay vnto you that they be your goſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dyſtroyers, that ſo counſelled you to commyt ydolatrye, whiche for the mayntenaunce of their naughty ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full lyfe, ſhut you out of the kynge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of god,<note place="margin">Mat. xxiii.</note> and wolde not ſuffre you to come therunto, neyther they them ſelues wolde entre into it. The kyngdome of god is taken in ſome
<pb facs="tcp:5745:39"/> places for his lyuely worde,<note place="margin">Luce. x.</note> his goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, hys glad tydynges whiche he brought to ſaue the worlde withall, through faythe in his paſſyon. For true it is that ye haue ben commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyd not to rede nor medle therwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, and they haue byn reputed and ſuffered as heretykes whiche haue preſumed to do contrarye to that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement. But nowe I praye you returne home agayn as the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dygall ſonne dyd vnto his father.<note place="margin">Luc. xv</note> Behold what a feaſt is prepared for you, couet no longer to be fed with the dregges of theyr tradycyons, whiche maye be reſymbled vnto the coddes that he wolde fayne haue ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of, amonge the ſwyne. Nowe do as he dyd returne home agayne, the table is layd, the goſpel of Chryſt is opened vnto you, come and ye ſhall here the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortable wordes of chriſt. what ioye ther is in heuen for a ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner that commyth to repentaunce.<note place="margin">Luc x<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>
               <pb facs="tcp:5745:40"/> Conſydre within youre ſelues whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ye haue not ben loſt in ſynne or not, when the fayth whiche ye ought to haue in Chriſt onely &amp; to be ſaued by the merytes of his paſſyon was deuyded and attributed parte vnto one ſaynt &amp; parte vnto an other as it appereth by ſekyng vnto the Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. Peraduenture ye wyl ſay we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leued in god, and we ſought y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ymage for goddes ſake. Whether ye pleaſed god therw<hi rend="sup">t</hi> or not ye ſhall here what he ſayd vnto Moyſes,<note place="margin">Deu. v. Exo. xx.</note> and to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Iſraell. I am the Lorde thy god, which hath brought the out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lande of Egypte out of the houſe of bondage.<note place="margin">Deu. viii.</note> Thou ſhalte haue none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther goddes in my ſyght, thou ſhalte make y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no grauen ymage of any ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of lykeneſſe of the thynges that are aboue in heuen and beneth vpon the erthe, nor in the water vnder the erthe. Thou ſhalte not honour them nor ſerue them, for I y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> lorde thy god
<pb facs="tcp:5745:40"/> am a ielouſe god vyſytyng the ſynne of the fathers vpon the chyldren to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thyrde and fourth generacyon of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that hate me,<note place="margin">Deu. xxxiiii.</note> and ſhewe mercy vpon many thouſandes of them that loue me and kepe my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementes. I ſtedfaſtly beleue that this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement dyd not alone perteyne vnto the chyldren of Iſraell, but vnto all men, and is to be obſerued of al thoſe whiche to the worldes ende beleueth Ieſus Chryſt the ſonne of god to be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſauyour of the world. Now ye that haue made theſe ymages honoured and worſhypped them conſydre with your ſelues whether ye haue not com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mytted the thyng which the chyldren of Iſrael were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mouth of god not to do. For I am ſure they are like to ſome thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aboue in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> erth beneth or in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> water vnder the erth. O lord y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye haue turned you fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lyuyng god vnto deed ymages which haue eyes &amp; ſe not, eares &amp; here not,
<pb facs="tcp:5745:41"/> noſes and ſmell not, handes and fele not, feyt and goo not, mouthes and ſpeake not, they are lyke vnto them whome the prophet Ieremy admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſſhed the people of Ieruſalem of,<note place="margin">Bar. vi</note> when they were led captyue into ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon, whether it be good or euyll that any man do vnto them. They are not able to recompe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce it,<note place="margin">Eccle. v</note> though a man make a vowe vnto them and kepe it not they wyll not requyre it. They can not delyuer a man frome deth, neyther are they able to defend the weake from the myghtye, they can not reſtore a blynde man to hys ſight, nor helpe any man at his nede, they can not ſhewe no mercye to the wydowe nor do good to the father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les,<note place="margin">Cap. xiiii</note> They muſt be borne vpon men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ſhulders, as thoſe that haue no feyt, wherby they declare vnto men that they be nothynge worth. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foundyd be they that worſhyp them for yf they fall to the grounde, they
<pb facs="tcp:5745:41"/> they can not ryſe vp agayne of them ſelues, when they be ſet vp in the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple theyr eies be ful of duſt through the feyt of them that come in, theyr faces wax blacke through the ſmoke that is in the temple. The owles, the ſwalowes and byrdes fle vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and the cattes ronne ouer theyr heades. They can not defende them ſelues frome the robbers and theues, the verye wycked are ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger then they, they ſtrepe them oute of theyr apparell that they be clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyd withall, they take theyr golde and ſyluer from them and get them awaye. yet can they not helpe them ſelues, they can gyue no ſentence of a matter nother defende the loude from wrong, to be ſhort they can not do ſo moche as a crowe that fleyth betwyxe heauen and earth. He con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludyth ſayenge blyſſed is the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly man that hath no ymage and wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhyppeth none,<note place="margin">Bar vi.</note> for he ſhalde far fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:5745:42"/> reproue. Many thynges haue I o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myttyd to wryte of, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tayned in this Epyſtle to the intente, that the myn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of thoſe whiche thynke I haue not wrytten truly. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcyence of them whiche haue ben and be yet combred with the execrable zele to venerate and worſhyp them may be mouyd to rede the ſame. Whome I inſtauntly deſyre alſo to pervſe the xiii. .xiiii. and .xv. Chapters of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pience, called the boke of wyſdome. And to reſorte vnto ſuche pſalmes &amp; places of ſcripture, as the cotacyons in the margent therof ſhall induſe you vnto, and I doute not but your co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcyence ſhalbe quyeted and ſatyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed in that matter, onles it be ſuche that obſtynatly wyl repugne agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt the ſryptures &amp; wyl of god. Whiche I cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vnworthy to be called chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans it ſhall alſo teſtefye vnto you, howe ſhamefullye ye haue ben moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked withal &amp; dyſceyued, &amp; what hath
<pb facs="tcp:5745:42"/> byn done w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the offryng money and other thynges offeryd vnto oure I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages. Thynke you it may not be verifyed, as Ieremy wrote vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that the preeſtes dyd adorne &amp; trime theyr harlottes, &amp; theyr chyldren w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al. I ſuppoſe verely there was but a ſmale porcyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therof gyuen vnto the ſyke and poore people. A lorde that thy people ſhuld ſo be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>dyd, that theyr offerynge vnto dee Images ſhuld be amayntenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce vnto quicke and deteſtable harlottes. This is the goodneſſe that comyth of youre pope holyneſſe. This is the profyte that commythe of youre payne and pope holye pylgrymage, whordome &amp; aduoutry is maynteyned through your Idolatrye. I thynke there is no faythful chryſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hert to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> god hath gyuen a mouth to ſpeake other a hand to wryte y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> can ſuffre this in iury againſt his lord god &amp; his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to be vnrebuked. Wherfore ſaye not
<pb facs="tcp:5745:43"/> that I rayle. For I ſuppoſe it is my parte and all chryſten mennes par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes not onlye to ſpeake and wryte a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt it, but hertelye to praye god to put in the rulers myndes to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme and route vp the occacyon of ſuche myſcheue. The lorde god be prayſed, the thyng is alredy gracy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſlye begon, whiche I hope ſhall haue lyke ſucceſſe &amp; endynge. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for loke vp ye that haue profeſt to be Chriſt. Let bales prophetes no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger dyſceaue you. I mean theſe wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked ſcole mayſters whiche throughe couetouſneſſe made you to beleue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> youre pylgrymage goynge and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frynge vnto Images was pleaſyng and acceptable vnto god. Where in verye dede it was playne Idolatrye and a mere madnes, to ſpeke vnto it that hathe no ſoule, and to make <note place="margin">Sapien xiiii.</note>petycyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto it for helth or lyfe that is deed to pray vnto it for helpe that is not able to helpe it ſelfe and for a
<pb facs="tcp:5745:43"/> good Iournye to hym that can not go. And when a man is on the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynge ſee or purpoſeth to ſayle ouer it to call for helpe vnto a ſtocke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is far weaker then the tre that beryth him.<note place="margin">Sapien xiiii.</note> 
               <note place="margin">gene. vi.</note> God cauſyd an arke to be made and therfore do men commy. theyr lyues to a ſmale pece of woode and are ſauyd.<note place="margin">Deu. iiii Deu. v.</note> But god commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded as ye haue rede before and as ye ſhall rede folowynge that Images ſhuld not be made. What meruayle is it then that the people often peryſſhe, whiche put more confydence in the thynge that the lord hath forbyden, then in the worke whiche the Lorde deuiſed and cauſed to be made. ye I maye ſaye (and lye not (then in the lorde hym ſelfe, as it often aperythe when through the mercye and onlye goodneſſe of god dyuers haue eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped the daungers perryles, and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynge tempeſt of the ſee. Go bare fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyd, bare legged, and in theyr ſhyrtes
<pb facs="tcp:5745:44"/> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dels and tapers to ſondry Ima<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges, whiche me thynke is a pytyfull ſyght amonges chryſten people ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng one god, the lord and creatour of all thynges, whom all creatures ought to honour and obey, put their truſte and confydence in, ſeke theyr helth and comforte at,<note place="margin">Deu. vi. Bar. v.</note> and that one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ought to be ſeruyd and worſhyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped. It is not moch to be meruayled at, and yf ther be many yet that mur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mour at the puttyng downe of ydo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrye, ſpecyally in them that are not learned in goddes worde. For it is harde ſodenly to roote out ſuperſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyous holyneſſe from the vnlearnyd peoples myndes, &amp; many of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſtes are very lothe to leſe theyr offerynge pence. For dyuers thynges can not be ſo wel mayntayned nowe as they were before. It was no lytle ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes of money that came yerelye to the preſtes ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des for offri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. To my Iudgement yf it had bene
<pb facs="tcp:5745:44"/> equally deuyded it wolde haue ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyſed to haue found al the poore and nedye beggers within thys realme. But yf I were a begger my ſelfe, tru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, I wolde be very lothe to be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de and kepte with that money offeryd vnto Idols. I had rather begge my brede in froffe and ſnowe, then to be kepte in a warme hoſpytall with it. Parauenture it wyl be obiected vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> our ymages ought not to be called ydols. And that the ſcrypture meaneth it not of them, but of ſuche as were in the olde tyme amonges the gentyls and hethen people what and yf I name them not Idols as theirs were called, but affyrme them to be Images and pyctures of ſayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. Whiche is the beſt name that can be gyuen them. yet yf ye knele and praye vnto them. I ſaye playnly that you co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myt ydolatry, chuſe whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ye wyll call them Idols or not
<pb facs="tcp:5745:45"/> For what ſoeuer it be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> robbeth chriſt from his due honour &amp; glory I count it to be an ydol though it be an yma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge of the beſt ſaynt that is in heuen. Saynt Paule ſayth that no fornyca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tour,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Cor. v. Ephe. vi</note> or vnclene perſone, or couetous perſone (whiche is a worſhypper of ydols) hath inherytaunce in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Chriſt. And in an other place he ſaythe howe agreeth the temple of god with ydols, ye are the temple of the lyuyng god,<note place="margin">ii. cor. vi</note> as ſayth god. Theſe are the admonicions of ſaynt Paule written in his epiſtles, alſo in dyuers other places, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtruct the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as ye lyſt &amp; chuſe whether ye wyll apply them to olde ydols eyther to newe ymages. And yf ther were no ymages in ſaynt Paules tyme, then muſte ye nedes graunt me that they were made ſyns And the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I pray you what place haue you in ſcrypture, that wyll ſtande w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you for the veneracyon and ſettyng
<pb facs="tcp:5745:45"/> vp of them. Remembre this ſayeng of Moyſes vnto the chyldren of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raell,<note place="margin">deu. iiii.</note> kepe wel your ſoules for ye ſaw no maner of ymage in the day when the lord ſpake vnto you out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyre vpon mount Horeb, that ye dyſtroy not your ſelues, and make you any ymage that is lyke a man or woman or beaſt vpon the erthe,<note place="margin">Deu. v.</note> or fethered foule vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heuen, or worme vpon the ground, or fyſſhe in the water vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der the erthe. &amp;c. Now truely this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dement doth nothyng aperteyn vnto you, onles ye take the god of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Iſaac, Iacob, Moyſes, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes, and of the chyldren of Iſrael to be your god yf you ſaye and beleue that he is your god, then do his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptes belonge vnto you, and not to you onely but vnto all that beleue in hym,<note place="margin">rom. iii.</note> for he is not a god vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iues onely, but to the gentyls alſo.</p>
            <p>¶O what pyte was it, when that
<pb facs="tcp:5745:46"/> poyſon was fyrſt ſhed in to the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che of Chryſt, when that papyſtycall honour was vſurped of the byſſhop of Rome to be aboue Emperoures, kynges and prynces. And when he fell from pouertye vnto pryde, falſly peruertynge the ſcryptures ſayenge that he mought bynde and loſe at his pleaſure. For then the ydolatry whiche Peter, Paule, and all the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles had wyped away with prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chynge of the worde of God, began to renewe agayne,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. xvi</note> Peters keyes wer chaunged, he began to playe checke mate with his mayſter, and ſet vp lawes and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtitucyons of his awne makynge. He graunted large indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences for vyſytynge ſaynt Peters ſee at Rome, and then other percey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge the profyte thereof opteyned pardons, for vyſytyng of ſyndry and dyuers other places. Then vp roſe, ydols, what ymages I ſhulde ſaye
<pb facs="tcp:5745:46"/> and Chriſt was deuyded. For where as the people helde hooly of hym,<note place="margin">i. Cor. i.</note> then began they to holde ſome of one ſaynt and ſome of an other, and ſoe haue contynued many yeres. But call to your remembraunce in whoſe name ye were baptyſed. Were ye bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyſed in Peters name, Paules name or Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s name, yf ye were, holde of them. If ye were chryſtened in chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes name, then holde of Chryſt and take hym for your ſauyoure, and his ſcrypture to wytneſſe for youre me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatoure.<note place="margin">i. timo. ii Heb. ix. Gyl iii<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Wherfore attrybute and gyue not vnto his ſayntes, that whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che onely is due to hym ſelfe. For yf ye do as I haue wrytten ſo wryte I agayne, theyr ymages ſo abuſed are but ydolles, and youre knelynge and prayenge before them is ydo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry. But I dowte not thoughe Chryſte haue ſuffered longe this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iury vnto hym ſelfe, and hys holy
<pb facs="tcp:5745:47"/> goſpell to be troden vnder fote,<note place="margin">ii cor. vi.</note> that nowe the acceptable tyme is come, ſo that his worde ſhall floryſſhe agayne in ſpyte of all the enemyes therof, &amp; that they ſhall not be able to abyde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tryall of the great wronge that they haue done vnto the people of god in kepyng away of the ſwete fruyt that they ſhuld haue had in his ſcrypture and to fede them with rotten apples &amp; foure crabbes of theyr awne trees. A ſtraw for your falſe fayned perſua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyons and lyes that haue taught the people to ſay, we honour not the yma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge but the ſaynt whome the ymage dothe repreſent. Why then do ye ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teme the ymage of our lady not in al places to be lyke, and dyuers yma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of one ſaynt to be lyke good. I mought more truely ſaye, to be lyke euyll. For as ye haue abuſed them, there was neuer a good, And to be more playne I can not ſe how ye can make them good, they that make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:5745:47"/> are lyke vnto them, and ſo are all ſuche as put theyr truſt in them.<note place="margin">Pſalm C.xiiii. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> xiiii.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Happy or bleſſed is the tree where through ryghtuouſneſſe cometh, but curſed is the ymage that is made w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> handes. For though it be not called god, yet is it a ſtale to robbe mennes hertes from God, and the honoure whiche alone dothe perteyne vnto God. O crafty catchpolles that ſoo haue inuented a name vnto them to be laye mennes bokes, whiche God hath prohybyted to be made, and to kepe from his people the boke of his lawe and his holy teſtament, the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes of the prophetes and appoſtles, and all the bokes of the holy fathers agreynge in one. (as I began this worke.) To inſtructe men the pertyt and true way vnto hym, whiche ſayd come vnto me all ye that labour and are laden and I ſhall refreſſhe you,<note place="margin">math. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> whiche he commaunded to be prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched and taught to his people, but
<pb facs="tcp:5745:48"/> be it now that I grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t you a ley that they were bokes to inſtructe the lay people.<note place="margin">mar xvi Math. xxviii</note> I am ſure theyr inſtruccy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on extendyd no farder but to put me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in remembraunce of them whome they do repreſent. What knowledge haue you by theyr deed and domme pycturs of theyr vertuous lyuyng. Suppoſe you they were ſo appare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in purple &amp; gold and ſo ſet with owchys, bedes, rynges, money, and other Iewels as theyr Images be, no truelye they regarded no ſuche peltrye. Theyr affeccyons were mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued to other more noble &amp; <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>cyouſſer thynges, for the pycture of hym y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye nowe garnyſſhe with golde, by his lyfe tyme was coueryd with a gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment made of Camels heare,<note place="margin">Mat. iii iiii. Re. i</note> and it is to be ſuppoſed (that as Chryſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prouyd them whiche buylded and <note place="margin">Lu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. xi. Mat. xxiii</note>garnyſſhed the Sepulcres of deed Prophettes whome theyr fathers
<pb facs="tcp:5745:48"/> had ſlayne) that ye lykewyſe whiche garniſſhe, gyld and ſpare for no coſt nowe vpon deed Images. Wolde ſcarſlye beſtowe one peny vpon the very ſayntes, yf they were lyuyng. For truelye theyr doctryne was the thynge whiche ye can not abyde to heare. Euen the Goſpell of Chryſte, that is nowe preachyd and taught vnto you. I wyll not faye that ye wold kyll them whiche haue ſuffred alredy for Chryſt and his doctryne. Whom ye accounte now to be ſayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, but yf they were lyuyng, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out fayle ye wolde repute and call them arrant herytykes. And then I thynke it ſhulde be a ſklendre chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te that ye wold byſtowe vpon them. But wherof happenyth this blynd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe amonges you, but that in ſtede of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true bokes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tained in ſcripture bothe of god and his ſayntes that preached taught &amp; folowed hym. ye haue ſet vp vnto you a blynde boke,
<pb facs="tcp:5745:49"/> a dome Idoll and a deed Image, whiche can inſtructe you to no good<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe, nor induce you to no vertue. Perchaunce there hanges ſome olde wrytten table by it, contaynyng ther in an abhomynable lye, and a falſe fayned myracle or twayne. But note one thynge I pray you, that wher ſo euer ſuche tables be, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> box to receyue offrynge monye is not or was not farre of, and yf that the box and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frynges be taken awaye, and none permytted to be any more ther, they that made and cauſed to be made youre blynde bokes, and lyenge ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, wold be more glad to pul them downe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your ſelues, ye they wold not pas yf ther were not one within chriſtendome. But I meruayle that they truſted not the ymage with the offrynge monye, what nede they to make ſo ſtrong boxys of yron or war dyd with plates of yron to kepe it. Me thynke yf the monye had byne
<pb facs="tcp:5745:49"/> layd but euen before the ymage, ther could no man haue taken it a waye but that his hande ſhulde haue cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to the aulter or to the place wher the money lay, yf they were ſo holye as they made them, but men maye perceaue they had but ſmale confy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> themſelues. yet taught they the people to ſeke helth at their handes whiche can do no good, nor ſay none euyll. For euery ſundry dyſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eaſe there was an ymage inuented and ſet vp. One for heed atche, an other for tothe atche. One for cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng, an other for burnyng. One for the palſay, an other for the plage. It were to longe a worke to reherce the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all. But yet me thynke it was great pyte that ſaynt Vncombre in poules was pulled down, for ſhe was a gret comforte and helper vnto all good wyues whiche were troubled with ſhrewde huſbandes. But I meruell for what purpoſe they offered otes
<pb facs="tcp:5745:50"/> vnto her me thynke that offerynge was more mete to be gyue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto ſaint Loy. For in ſome partes of England the horſe cutters haue .v. pence for cuttyng of euery horſe a grote to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfe &amp; a peny for ſaint Loye. It is to be thought he was ſome horſe keper or horſe corſer, wherfore otes were more mete to fede his horſſes withall then to be offered to ſaynt vncumbre it is no meat conuenient for a woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to fede of. I praye you good women be not dyſpleaſed with me for my playne wrytynge. And if ony of you be troubled with an euyll huſbande, the beſt counſel that I can gyue you is to ſhewe your ſelfe ſo kynde, lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge, and meke vnto him, that he maye be aſhamed (oneleſſe he be paſt all ſhame) But to be good and gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyl vnto you. It doth not belonge vnto my matter to treate betwyxte men and theyr wyues. And alſo for lacke of experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce becauſe I was
<pb facs="tcp:5745:50"/> neuer maryed) It mought chaunce wher as I purpoſe to pleaſe one that I ſhuld diſpleaſe .ii. Wherfore I wyl reſorte to my purpoſe. deſyryng both men and women to thynke as the trueth is, that any thynge whiche is wrytten in thys lytle volume concer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nynge ſayntes that it is not wrytten in their diſpraiſe, nother yet in the diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>prayſes of ſuche perſons which haue ben blinded (through falſe ypocrites) with ſuperſtycyous holyneſſe. Nowe knowledgynge in their hertes their folly and blindneſſe, receauynge the trueth that is declared vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For ther were very fewe whiche haue not wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dered in darkeneſſe. But to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> gods holy doctrine can take no place whoſe ſtomakes are ſo ful ſtuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed vp with ſyn &amp; abominable Idola<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>try that their eares can not here ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther theyr eies behold y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word of god. But obſtinatly refuſe it, repugne a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gaynſt it, &amp; ſpeake euyll of it, callyng
<pb facs="tcp:5745:51"/> it newe doctryne) I can not ſe but they are to be dyſprayſed and lamen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted as people frowardly refuſynge the grace of the holy ghoſt offered vnto them, but ye that are the people of god and haue receyued the lyght of his goſpel, remembre that ye haue ben deceyued. Let it neuer fall from youre myndes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye haue walked in darkeneſſe,<note place="margin">Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. ii</note> &amp; nowe that the lyght is come whiche hath bene longe kepte fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you. Worke whyle ye haue light ſome haue loſt their lyues for ſotting forth of it. And many haue auentu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red their lyues (ſcapyng very narow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly) before they could bring it to paſſe. Be ye buſy therfore in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lordes har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt,<note place="margin">Luce. x.</note> the harueſt is great and the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers are fewe, for there be many ydle bely beaſtes that couyt to haue the nyght come agayne, whiche lyſte not to laboure but ſlepe in ſynne as they and other haue done before, but becauſe I haue yet made no full and
<pb facs="tcp:5745:51"/> perfyte anſwere to them which haue ceduſed the people from the true ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourynge of God vnto ymages (for theyr fylthy lucre) ſayenge and tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chyng them to ſay. We went not in pilgrymage vnto the ymage nor we prayed not vnto the ymage, but we went for the ſayntes ſake whom the ymage dothe repreſent, &amp; we prayed vnto the ſaynt whiche is in heuen. ye thynke that this is ſo ſtronge a reaſon that no man can avoyde it. But ſure ther is nothynge that can be cloked agaynſt the worde of God whiche wyll not be eſpyed, and is ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſye ynoughe to be auoydyd. I praye you aunſwere me fyrſt for what pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe ye prayed vnto the ſaynte, the ſaynt can not ſaue you. ye are not of god onleſſe ye beleue to be ſauyd by the merytes and paſſyon of Chryſte only. The beſt of al the ſayntes could not ſaue him ſelfe by his owne mery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, no yf ony of them were leſſe ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners
<pb facs="tcp:5745:52"/> then you are, it was by grace gyuen them of god and not of theyr awne powers. And I am ſure they are no ſaintes onleſſe they do attry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute the gyfte to come of god onely, ye wyll ſaye becauſe they are in ſuche fauoure with god, therfore wyll we praye vnto them that they maye be mediatours vnto god for vs. Nowe here aperyth a lacke of knoweledge of you in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcrypture. And if ye know it a lacke of ſure faythe and truſte to beleue it.<note place="margin">Timo. ii</note> For ſaynt Paule ſayeth ther is one god and one mediatoure be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twyxte god and man, whiche is the man Chriſt Ieſus. What miſtruſte haue you in him, thynke ye that he is not a ſufficyent mediatour for vs al. He hathe made vs a promys y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> what<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſoeuer we axe of the father in hys name it ſhall be gyuen vs.<note place="margin">Ioh xv.</note> All the ſaintes that be in heuen neuer made vs ſuche a promys for it is oute of theyr powers to perfourme it, they
<pb facs="tcp:5745:52"/> they them ſelues ſtacke to that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe. they had neuer come in heuen els. I neuer redde of any of the ſayntes when they were here lyuyng that made ony praiers to the ſayntes whiche were deed before them, but al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>waies vnto god, is god of leſſe pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er or goodneſſe then he was in olde tyme. It is euen the ſame god, it is he that brought the children of Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell oute of bondage frome the cruell Pharao kynge of Egypte throughe the greate ſee,<note place="margin">Ex. iiii. Ioſu. ii. Iudi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Pſalm. lxxvii. Ge. x<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ii. i. Cor. x.</note> whiche he deuyded lyke a wall on euery ſyde, ſoo that they walked throughe as on the dry lande, it is he that gaue them water oute of the harde ſtone it is he that fedde them with Manna in wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe,<note place="margin">Exo. xx.</note> it is he that brought them vnto the fruyteful and goodly londe that he promyſed them,<note place="margin">Deu. vi. Ioſue. xxiiii.</note> it is the ſame God that perfourmed all his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſes to all thoſe that faythfullye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted in him, &amp; obſerued his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dementes.
<pb facs="tcp:5745:53"/> And yf ye thynke hys power be as good now as it was the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and euer hath bene, why ſeke ye not to him, why ſeke ye for helthe at other mennes ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des. What can y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayntes do more for you now, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they coulde do for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whiche in tyme paſte put the irtruſt holli in God. Perchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ye thynke youre ſelues vnworthy by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of your ſynn to pray vnto god, and therfore ye wyll deſyre the ſayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes to pray for you. And yf ye be of that mynde it doth apere ye haue a dyſtruſte in the promys and mercye of god. If ye turne vnto me ſaythe Chryſt I wyll turne vnto you.<note place="margin">Zacha. i. Ier. xxx<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Pſalm. xxiiii.</note> The prophet ſayth what ſoeuer he be that feareth the Lorde he ſhall ſhewe him the way that he hath choſen.<note place="margin">Pſ. xxvi</note> Delyte thou in the lorde &amp; he ſhall gyue the thy hertes deſyre.<note place="margin">Pro. xvi</note> Salomon ſaythe commyt thy workes vnto the Lorde and loke what thou deuyſites it ſhal proſper, and yf ye turne not vnto the
<pb facs="tcp:5745:53"/> Lord, feare hym &amp; delyte in hym w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a repentaunt mynd for youre naugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye ſynfull lyfe. In vayne is youre prayer and all youre deuyſes, for ye ought to commyte your workes vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to the Lorde, in whom onlye ye haue not one promyſe, but manye promy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes agreyng in one (contayned in the ſcriptures) to proſper and to be hard. And to optayn your requeſtes of god the father for Chryſtes ſake,<note place="margin">Ioh. xv.</note> and not for ony of the deed ſayntes ſakes, But yet trwe it is that God ſpared the punnyſhement of ſynners, and hylde his hande frome plagynge of them often tymes for the iuſte men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ſakes as ye may rede how Moy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes pacyefyed the dyſpleaſure of god agaynſt the people with his prayer.<note place="margin">Exod. xxxii.</note> Which was made fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuch a faithful hert vnto god. And for ſuche a true louynge mynd vnto his people, that he deſyred (rather then they ſhuld be dyſtroyed) to be ſtryken oute of the
<pb facs="tcp:5745:54"/> boke of lyfe himſelfe. Paule wyſſhed alſo to be curſed frome Chriſt for his brethrens ſake.<note place="margin">Rom. i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Theſe praiers were of another maner effect the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prayers of our popeholy pykepurſes, prayng for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoules in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bitter paynes of pur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gatory. Agayne ye maye rede y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> god wolde haue ſpared y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dyſtruccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eyties which were dyſtroyed for ſyn,<note place="margin">Gene. xviii.</note> for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſakes of te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> good perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, yf they mought haue ben founde in them, at the requeſt of Abraham. Remembre the exortacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſaynt Iames,<note place="margin">I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>. v.</note> for one man to praye for an other declaryng what efficacy is in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ryghtuous ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes praier if it be ferue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. By example of Helyas that was a man mortall euen as we are,<note place="margin">iiiii Reg xvii.</note> whiche tolde kynge Achab y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it ſhulde not rayne, &amp; it ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned not on the earthe by the ſpace of iii. yeres and .vi. monethes, and he prayed agayne,<note place="margin">iiii. Reg xviii.</note> and the heuen gaue raine, &amp; the erth brought forth fruyt. I wold y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people wolde be exercyſed
<pb facs="tcp:5745:54"/> in redyng &amp; heryng ſuch lyke ſtories whiche mought put them in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the great mercy &amp; goodnes of god alwayes ſhewed vnto them which did feare &amp; loue him, &amp; what ef<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fecte their prayers were of. Wherin they mought alſo take exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple what puniſſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t god toke vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> obſtinate ſynners &amp; ydolatres, whiche though god ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpared to punyſſhe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ryghtuous me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes ſakes, &amp; at theyr hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble &amp; ferue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t prayers yet is ther to be notyd in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all after what ſorte &amp; maner god ſparyd them. Salomon whiche had commytted Idolatrye &amp; diſpleaſed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lorde, agaynſt who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> god rayſed vp ſundry aduerſaries to trou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble him &amp; his kyngdome. yet y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lorde ſpared him &amp; made him a promyſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſhulde poſſeſſe ſtyll his lande du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe his lyfe,<note place="margin">iiii. Reg xi.</note> for his father dauids ſake which had walked in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wayes of the lorde, but there was no promiſe made vnto him y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſhulde inheryte
<pb facs="tcp:5745:55"/> the kyngedome of heauen for his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſake. I am ſure he neuer came ther but yf it were for Chryſtes ſake only. Nother the beſt ſaynt that euer dyed, ſo where ye fynde that god ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed his mercy vpon ſynners for the ryghtuous me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes ſakes. Conſyder alwayes the diuerſyte of the benefite gyuen only for Chryſtes ſake (which is the kyngdome of heauen) and that whiche was gyuen at the petycyons and for the loue of holye men, beynge but a temporall rewarde, it is but a temporall rewarde for a man to haue his lyfe prolonged. Neyther to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy landes, ryches, honoure, helth, or ſuche other thynges.<note place="margin">mar. xvi Act. v.</note> The apoſtles by theyr lyfe tyme receaued power of the lorde to gyue helthe to them that were ſycke. And to caſte out deuyls and vnclen ſpyrytes.<note place="margin">iiii. Be. xvii.</note> yee and ye ſhal rede of holy men that by theyr pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers haue reuyuyd the deed to lyfe. yet al theſe were but temporal benefites
<pb facs="tcp:5745:55"/> gyuen alſo of hym by his ſayntes to confyrme theyr faythe in his name that they dyd it (whiche is Chriſte) to whome belongeth only the remiſſion of ſynnes and the kyngdome of god.<note place="margin">Rom. v.</note> Now ſeyng it belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth onlye to him to gyue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one, &amp; to forgyue the other they ought onely to be requyred and deſyred of him. And if ye purpoſe to praye vnto the deed ſaintes for any thing belongynge either to your bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes or ſoules vpon the grounde of this argument, ſayeng for as moche as they were holye men and women in theyr tyme, and that god ſpared the punyſſhment of ſynners often for their ſakes, and at the feruente and humble prayers, moche rather it is to be thought that they now hauing receauid a glorified body, and be in ioye with Chriſt ſhalbe herde of the lord. And the ſinners ſparyd at their requeſt and prayers. To that I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere yf ye were certayne that the
<pb facs="tcp:5745:56"/> ſayntes whiche are deed (whoſe bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes remayne in the earthe to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurruccyon of all fleſſhe) do aſwell heare your voyces nowe, as they did the voyces of the people beinge here and ſpekyng vnto them by their lyfe tyme. That then it were conuenyent ye ſhulde praye vnto them to praye with you and for you to god. But for as moche as I neuer yet could be certefied by ony man throughe ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture that they do heare oure prayers, for my parte I thinke it but a vayne thinge to truſte in the vncertayne thinge, and to leue the certayne, to leue Chriſt and praye to his ſaintes. To all thoſe that knowe the ſaintes heres them I ſaye it is well done, but to al them that beleue it and know it not, I ſaye it is not well done. For as moche as they haue not the ſcryp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture to certefy the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their wel doing. The vnlearned multytude exceptyd in whome I thynke it is nother wel
<pb facs="tcp:5745:56"/> nor euyll done, whiche knowe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is preached &amp; taught by their curates vnto them. So they refuſe not the truth (aproued by ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture) when it is taught them, whiche I refer vnto the biſſhoppes and wel learned men in the ſcriptures wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>in is contayned al thynges neceſſary belongynge to faith and ſaluacion. But admyt that ye were certayne y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſayntes do heare you (whiche I thynke trulye wolde trouble the mooſte parte of the clergye within Englande to approue) ſuppoſe you that they wold pray either with you or for you if ye thynke euyll in youre harte, not beyng pourged with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricion for ſyn, and to praye for good thynges with your mouthe, no tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly onles they do only heare the voyce and knowe not the harte. But God whiche hearethe the voyce and kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth the ſecretes of the mynde,<note place="margin">Ro. viii.</note> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardeth neither the honoure whiche
<pb facs="tcp:5745:57"/> ye gyue him, neither the prayer of your mouth onles your hertes agre withall and if you praye for grace with your mouth, and couyt it with all your hertes, it ſhalbe gyuen you yf you pray forgyueneſſe of your ſyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes &amp; are penytent for them in youre hertes they ſhalbe forgyue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you. Axe what ſoeuer ye wyll (in faithe) and it ſhalbe graunted vnto you.<note place="margin">Ioh. xv</note> But in whoſe name ye ſhulde aſke, I haue ſhewed you and for his ſake ther is a promis made vnto you y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye ſhall obtayn it. It is not for ſaynt frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cis ſake that ye ſhall poſſes the celeſtial heritage nother yet his holye cowle that can preſerue you frome hell (for your ſinnes) let the frers ſay as they liſt. It is a vayne reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that I haue harde dyuers men make, which by a ſimilitude apply y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fauour of world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly princes vnto the fauour of the ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtial god ſayeng if a man haue any thing to do with the kinge, he muſt
<pb facs="tcp:5745:57"/> fyrſte ſue vnto the noble men of the courte, and ſuche as be of the kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges preuy chambre, yf he thynke to opteyne his purpoſe, &amp; not to preaſe to the kyng hym ſelfe. And ſo lyke<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wyſe vnto God a man ſhulde fyrſte pray and be a ſueter vnto his ſayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes &amp; not preſume to go to hym ſelfe. Is not this an vnwyſe thynge that men pondre no better the dyuerſyte betwyxte the creator of all thynges and his creatures. The kynges gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce is the miniſtre of god, and yet but a man as an other man is, his know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge maye not be compared to the knowledge of god.<note place="margin">Ro viii Hiere. x<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vii. pſal. vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> God knoweth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſecretes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> herte, the kyng knowes it not before it be vttered and tolde hym. And he that is the kynge of a realme hath many thinges to thinke on ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a man hath nede to make his frendes aboute hym yf he thynke for to ſpede, and euery man maye not at al tymes come to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kynges preſence.
<pb facs="tcp:5745:58"/> But to come vnto God is an other maner of thynge, ſo that thou come with an vmble, a meke, &amp; a contryte herte, for god is neuer troubled with buſyneſſe, all thynges are vnto him but as one thyng. And though he be kynge of all kynges, yet is he well pleaſed that thou ſhalte come to hym at all tymes, there is no porter nor dore keper ſhall kepe the oute. If y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> loue him he wyll be alwayes where as y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> arte. Thou canſt not ſpeake ſo ſoftly but he ſhal heare y<hi rend="sup">u</hi>.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. viii.</note> Thou ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt thynke nothynge, but he knoweth thy thought, and if y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> aſke any thyng in faythe thou arte ſure to haue it,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> he byddeth the come to hym, he ſendeth the to none other. Wherfore ſhul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt thou be afrayde to do as he byd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the. And ſeyng that people haue founde oute ſo ſtronge a reaſon to ſtande on, I wyll aſſaye to ſtoppe their mouthes with an other reaſon.</p>
            <p>Who wolde not thynke hym to be
<pb facs="tcp:5745:58"/> a fole or an hartleſſe perſon to whom the kynge wolde ſaye. If thou haue any thynge to demaunde of me ſpea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke to me thy ſelfe, and I wyll gyue the thy requeſt. And yf he wolde not ſpeake vnto the kyng hym ſelfe, but deſyre an other to ſpeake for hym, of the whiche he were vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne whether the kynge wolde here hym or not, were it not an vnwyſe parte. Alſo yf the kynge wolde ſaye, there ſhall none come in to my preuy chambre, But ſuche as my ſonne the prynce ſhall ſuffre to come in. (take it that his grace were come to his perfyte yeres of knowledge and perſeueraunce. And yf I mou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghte ſpeake vnto the Prynce and were ryghte certayne to come in<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> when I deſyred hym. Were not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a foole to deſyre an other to ſpeake vnto the prynce for me, which I were vncertayn whether the prynce wold
<pb facs="tcp:5745:59"/> here hym or not. Now ſeing we haue none other enteraunce in to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God the father, but by his ſonne Ieſus Chriſt, &amp; he hath ſayd. Come to me, why ſhuld we go to any other,<note place="margin">Mat. xi</note> but to hym ſelfe onely. I wold haue ben lothe to bryng in theſe hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne reaſons to eſtabliſſhe goddes worde withall, had I not ben com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled (as the ſayeng is) to dryue out one nayle with an other, one reaſon with an other. The worde of God dothe informe you, who is your me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatour plucke no honour away that is due vnto hym. Haue no leſſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence in hym the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye ought to haue. All that apperteyneth to hym by the ſcryptures gyue it hym, and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your conſciencys trulye examined yf ther remayne ony thynge belongynge to the ſayntes, gyue it them and ſpare not. But where ye fynde him to be your onely ſauiour and mediatoure,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Thi. ii</note> patche him not vp I pray you with
<pb facs="tcp:5745:59"/> his ſayntes. And if ye lyſt to pray vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to them, lerne fyrſt to be acerteyned whether they heare you or not, that you labour no longer in vayne. And proue it eyther a thynge inuentyd to rob Chriſt fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his glory, &amp; you from your money, other els y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it came of a diſtruſt in the promiſes &amp; mercyfull goodneſſe of god. But to ſaye or thynke that our lady is not in al pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces lyke good, bleſſyd, and holye, or ony ſaint better in one place then in an other. And ſo to go to theyr Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and pictures, ſettynge vp of can<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dels, knelynge, kiſſynge, prayenge, &amp; off<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ryng vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> I ſay playnly is ydolatry, &amp; for ydolatry god hath puniſſhed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people often tymes with diuers and ſundry plages. For ydo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry he ſpared not kynges and prin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces, but rooted their poſterites from their kyngedomes.<note place="margin">iii. Reg. xiiii. iii Reg. xv. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vi</note> As ye maye rede of Ieroboam, kynge Achab and dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers other. Nowe ſeynge that the
<pb facs="tcp:5745:60"/> lorde ſpared not kynges and rulers of the earth for ydolatry, which were in the tyme that the law of god gyue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto Moyſes ſtode onely in effecte, beyng in dyuers thynges but fygu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res &amp; ſhadowes of the true and very Meſſias (which is Ieſus Chriſt) and we hauyng his moſt holy teſtament, a wytneſſe vnto vs that he hathe all redy ſuffered for the redempcyon of our ſynnes.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Pet. ii</note> Shall we ſuppoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he wyl ſpare vs for ydolatry if we repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t not &amp; conuert vnto hym (no truely) but let vs wayte for a greter punyſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they had. For the lord god ſayd I came not to breake the lawe,<note place="margin">Mat. v. Deu. v.</note> but to fulfyll the lawe. And where as Moyſes ſayd, thou ſhalte not kyll. Chriſt ſayd,<note place="margin">Exo. xx.</note> thou ſhalt not be angry. Moyſes ſayd, thou ſhalte not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myt aduoutry. Chriſt ſayth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> who ſoeuer eyeth a wyfe luſtyng after her hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mytted aduoutry w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> her alredy in his hert.<note place="margin">Leui. ix</note> ye haue herde how it is ſayd
<pb facs="tcp:5745:60"/> thou ſhalt loue thy neyghbour &amp; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te thyne enemy. But chriſt ſayeth vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to you, loue your enemyes,<note place="margin">Mat. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> bleſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> curſe you, do good to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that hate you, pray for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that do you wrong. &amp; perſecute you, that you may be the chyldren of your heuenly father, for he maketh his ſonne to ryſe on the euyll &amp; on the good, and ſendeth his rayne on the iuſt and on the vniuſt, wherin it apereth what a mercyfull God he is. But beware ye that are nowe paſt the tyme of the ſhadowes and figures of Moyſes lawe, &amp; haue the very thynge offered vnto you, whiche all thoſe fygures &amp; ſhadowes dyd repreſent. For yf ye froward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly refuſe it, and ſtyll folowe youre owne blynde wayes, and the inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyons of thoſe that ſoughte youre dyſtruccyon, and wyll not herken vnto hym that ſayde.</p>
            <p>I am the waye, the trueth,<note place="margin">Ioh xiiii</note> and the lyfe. It is greatly to be feared, that
<pb facs="tcp:5745:61"/> as the children of Iſraell vnto who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ther was a terreſtiall and temporall kyngedome promiſed (that goodlye lande of Canaan) whiche was full of all pleaſures and comodites for brea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kynge of the Lorrdes preceptes and chefly for Idolatry,<note place="margin">Exo. iii</note> were puniſſhed with diuers temporall plages and punniſſhmentes. So lyke caſe that ye whiche haue the celeſtiall kynge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome promiſed vnto you, where ther are ſuche thynges prepared for them that loue god, which the eye hath not ſene and the eare hath not herde nor hath it entred in to the herte of man.<note place="margin">i. Co. ii. Eſa. l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iiii</note> If ye wyll not obſerue the lordes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dementes, but prouoke hym ſtyl vnto diſpleaſure with your ydolatry as I ſayd, it is to be feared, leſt your punyſſhment be reſerued vnto that place,<note place="margin">Math. xiiii.</note> where there ſhall be waylynge and gnaſſhyng of tethe. Call your iniquites to remembraunce, expell your ſynne and ydolatry with repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce.
<pb facs="tcp:5745:61"/> Be not ſtyffe necked agaynſt the lorde whiche ſtandeth waytynge that he may haue mercy vpon you, &amp; lifteth hym ſelfe vp y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> he may receyue you to grace.<note place="margin">Eſa. xxi</note> As the prophet Eſaye ſayd vnto the people of god whiche were punyſſhed, for ſekyng helpe at other then hym ſelfe, for the lord god is ryghtuous, happy are al they that wayte for hym. Marke that ſayeng of the prophet, he ſayd not happy are ſome, but happy are all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wayte for hym. And though the wordes were ſpoken vnto the people of Cyon, and to the Cyteſens of Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yet doth it ſerue alſo vnto vs. For he is our lorde and our God, of whom it was ſayd vnto them, ſhall ye neuer be in heuyneſſe, for dowtles he wyll haue mercy vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you.<note place="margin">Eſa. xxx</note> As ſone as he hereth the voyce of thy cry he wyl helpe the. The Lorde gyueth you the breed of aduerſyte, and the water of trouble, but thyne inſtructour flyeth not far
<pb facs="tcp:5745:62"/> from y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> yf thyne eyes loke vnto hym, yf thyne eares herke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto his word, that cryeth after y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> and ſayeth. This is the way, go this, &amp; tourne the ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the ryght hande nor to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lyft. ye ought to put nothyng to the word of god nor to take no thyng from it,<note place="margin">Deu. iiii</note> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord wold haue you kepe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtreight path which is apoynted vnto you by the ſcrypture. As for the tradycyons of men they be dowtfull &amp; in many thynges not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſonaunt vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Haue ye not ben taught to ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vp ſuche prayers, wherof ye vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtode not one word what ye ſayd. The apoſtle ſayeth yf I praye with tonges (meanyng a voyce y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtode not) my ſpyryte prayeth but my mynde is without fruyte. I had leuer in the congregacyon to ſpeake. v. wordes with my mynde to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formacyon of other,<note place="margin">i, Cor. xiiii</note> rather then .x. thouſande wordes with the tonges (whiche be not vnderſtande.) The
<pb facs="tcp:5745:62"/> effecte of prayer ꝑſiſteth not in many wordes. Chriſt ſayeth,<note place="margin">Mat. vi</note> when ye praye bable not moche as the Gentyls do, for they thynke they ſhal be herde for theyr moche bablyng ſake. Be ye not lyke them therfore, for youre father knoweth wherof ye haue nede before ye aſke of hym.<note place="margin">Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> The ſcrybes and pha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>raſyes were reproued of the lorde for teachyng the people to obſerue theyr tradycyons in ſtede of goddes pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptes, ſayenge.<note place="margin">Eſe. xix</note> Well prophecyed Eſaye of you, with theyr lyppes they honoure me, but theyr herte is farre fro me. And where the worde of God is truely preached the ſame word ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke wyſe ſhall reproue your falſe tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers whiche haue taught you and youre fathers th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s many yeres wyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked tradycyons.<note place="margin">Mat. vi.</note> The true faſtynge and perfyte prayer haue they abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and taughte the people to doo lykewyſe the workes of charyte and almous dede (whiche oughte to be
<pb facs="tcp:5745:63"/> done and gyuen to the poore) hathe ben dymynyſſhed and gyuen to ſtur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy and valyaunt beggers craftely crepte in to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church of Chriſt, which haue begyled the people with theyr falſe ypocryſy and fayned holyneſſe. Meruayll not though it greue them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the people haue fre lyberty to rede and ſerche the ſcriptures, for it is the onely thyng that vttereth theyr craft theyr falſhode, &amp; theyr wyckedneſſe, for betwyxte them and theyr ydolles which were inuented to pyke me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes purſes (and that vnder an holy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence) what meruayl was it that En<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gland was ſo replenyſſhed with the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, vacabundes and beggees, it is an euydent thing that the moſt parte of them be offended that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcrypture is in Englyſſhe, wherby their ſubtel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye is eſpied, for if a man reproue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ypocryſy, or byd them laboure for their lyuynge. Awe ſay they is this y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> charyte that the goſpel teacheth you.
<pb facs="tcp:5745:63"/> Truely it were not to be wondred at yf men were not ſo moche in charyte with you as they be whiche ſo haue dyſceyued the pore ſymple ſoules fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theyr charytable aimous, to whome god dyd apoynt it to be gyuen. I ſay not this becauſe men ſhulde breake their pacyence towardes you, but to reduce you the ſoner to repentaunce and amendement, and to be ſory and aſhamed of your euyll doynges. Saynt Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſayeth in his ſeconde Epyſtle who ſo tranſgreſſeth &amp; aby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doctryne of Chriſt hath not god, he that abydeth in the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryne of Chriſt hath bothe the father and the ſonne. If any man come to you and bryng not this doctryne, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue hym not in to your houſe ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſalute hym. That text I ſuppoſe cauſed the freres to ronne aboute w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> In principio erat verbum, fearynge els they ſhulde not be ſaluted of the peple nor receyued i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to theyr houſes.
<pb facs="tcp:5745:64"/> But there is an other place in ſcryp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture more conuenyent to be applyed vnto them then y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> place agreed and ſerued to their purpoſe, beware of fal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe ꝓphetes which come to you in ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes clothyng, but inwardly they are rauenyng wolues, ye ſhal know the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by their fruytes, God knoweth my herte I write this for no malice vnto them, but to thentent y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the truthe of gods glory which hath long ben hyd mought appere agayne, &amp; his holy goſpel which they &amp; ſuche other haue falſly belyed, peruerted &amp; kepte in cor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ners may come to his perfyte lyght, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the people myght know the true honouryng of God to be in ſpirite &amp; veryte, &amp; to folow the exhortacyon of ſaynt Peter to walke after the wyl of god &amp; not after the wyll of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hethen,<note place="margin">i. Pe. iii.</note> in wantonnes, ryotous drynkyng, &amp; abhomynable ydolatry, &amp; the holſom counſell of ſaynt Paule to be no wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhipper of ymages,<note place="margin">Collo. i.</note> &amp; to mortefy your membres
<pb facs="tcp:5745:64"/> of ſynne vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth.<note place="margin">Iohn. v.</note> Saynt Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> warneth lytel chyldren to kepe them ſelues from ymages. O lorde howe hath thy bleſſed worde &amp; the doctrine of thy holy ſayntes ben abuſed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> old me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> now a days ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſcarſly be brought to folow y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leſſon. Know ye not y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> your body is the temple of the holy ghoſt.<note place="margin">i Cor. vi.</note> Remembre vpon what foundacyon ye are buylded,<note place="margin">Mat. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>i. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> ſtycke vnto your fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dacyon &amp; cleue faſt to your heed cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſtone, which can not be remoued. ye are not a temple of ſtone made w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> mennes handes, ye are y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lyuyng tem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple of god,<note place="margin">ii Cor. vi</note> whiche haue ben longe in decay, bruſed, broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; pulled downe of thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wer enemyes bothe to you &amp; your foundacyon Chriſt,<note place="margin">Mat <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> i. Cor. iii</note> but they haue pulled ſo long, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they haue met w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a rocke,<note place="margin">1 Pet. ii.</note> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtomblyng ſtone whiche hath made them to fall. Now is the tyme to repayre your temple agayne be ye not neclyge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lordes worke, but laboure w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> herte &amp; mynde, therin
<pb facs="tcp:5745:65"/> euery man according to his power &amp; callyng. And agaynſt ſuche as wyll go aboute to hyndre or let the going forth of your worke, prouyde watch men (I meane preachers) to defende you with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worde of god as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people dyd at the buyldyng agayn of Ieru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſalem w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> weapons,<note place="margin">ii. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>. iiii</note> &amp; ſome labouring w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> one hand hauyng their weapons in the other hand. So ye that are la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers in what ſcyence ſo euer it be (to gete your lyuyng w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> trouthe, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordyng to the wyll of god) yf ye can handle your weapon, yf ye haue any knowledge in the ſcriptures, then let the lawe of god, his holy teſtament &amp; bleſſed word (beyng the ſworde that Chriſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded his dyſcyples to by) be alwayes redy at your hande,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xii</note> whether ye eate or drynke, ſlepe or wake, go or ride, ye whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye be at your lawfull workes, &amp; in all places haue it in a redynes, to reſyſt therwith the enemyes of the lordes worke (which
<pb facs="tcp:5745:65"/> wolde not haue his holy temple re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payred agayne.) Beholde what an ouerſeer &amp; mayſter of your worke, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lorde your god hath choſen &amp; apoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto you our moſt gracious ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g a true defender of the fayth of Chriſt &amp; his churche, agaynſt the wrongful violatours therof. And for becauſe he wolde not take y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name in vayne (craftely giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to his grace to ſupport &amp; maynteyn a church which is agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt chriſt) (depriuyng prynces from their iuſt tytle &amp; true name.) He hath take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vpon hym (as the law of god permyt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teth) to be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſupreme heed of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church vnder god, which was not only faiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vſurped from his grace &amp; his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyceſſours, but alſo fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al other kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges &amp; prynces. Reioyce &amp; be mery all ye which haue ben as ſhepe goyng a ſtray.<note place="margin">i. Pet. ii. Luce. xv Eſa. liii</note> But now retourned agayne to your byſſhop &amp; ſhepeherde of youre flocke, &amp; they that be not come, let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> come &amp; herken vnto his voyce, &amp; to
<pb facs="tcp:5745:66"/> theyr voyces whom he hathe ſent to call them. Let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no longer diſceyue you which ſent you to deed ymages no nor yet to the ſayntes to be youre aduocates. Our aduocate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s Iheſus Chriſte.<note place="margin">i. Ioh. ii</note> whiche optayneth grace for our ſynnes, and not for our ſynnes onely but for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſynnes of all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world. Serche the ſcriptures and ye ſhal ſe howe wrongfully &amp; falſly they haue belyed it bothe agaynſt god and ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For where they haue borne kynges &amp; prynces in hande that yf the people ſhulde be ſuffered to haue it in theyr maternall tonge that it wolde make them heretykes to god, &amp; diſobedient vnto theyr gouernours. There is no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thyng more true then this is an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homynable lye, a very blaſphemy to god, and treaſon to kynges, for it is the onely perfyte thyng, that tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth men theyr true obedyence and duety, bothe to god, to the prynces &amp; to ther gouernours.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> iii.</note> Saynt Paule
<pb facs="tcp:5745:66"/> wrote vnto Titus ſayeng, warne the people that they ſubmyt them ſelues vnto prnyces, and to the hyer aucto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, to obey y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> officers, &amp; to be redy vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to al good workes.<note place="margin">Ro. xiii.</note> And vnto the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maynes, let euery ſoule ſubmyt hym ſelfe vnto the hyer powers, for there is no power but of god. In the ſame chapter he ſayeth, gyue to euery man therfore his duety trybute to whome tribute belongeth, cuſtome to whom cuſtome is due, feare to whom feare belongeth,<note place="margin">i. Pet. ii.</note> honour to whom honour perteyneth. Saynt Peter ſayeth ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myt your ſelues vnto all maner or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denaunces of men, whether it be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the kynge as vnto the chyef heed, or vnto rulers as vnto them that are ſent of hym, for the punyſſhment of euyll doers. But for the prayſe of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that do wel, honour al men loue bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly felowſhyp. Feare god, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour the kyng. And Chriſt hym ſelfe ſayd vnto the diſcyples of the phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,<note place="margin">mat. xxii</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:5745:67"/> whiche were ſent to tangle hym in his wordes, concernynge trybute to be payde vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Emperour. Gyue vnto Ceſar that whiche is Ceſars, &amp; gyue vnto god that whiche is gods. Many mo places are ther conteyned in the ſcryptures, to eſtablyſſhe and confyrme my ſayenges to be trewe, teachyng the people the trewe loue &amp; feare of god, and the iuſt obedience &amp; honour of prynces, and ſuche as be in auctoryte. But I truſt that this ſhall ſuffyſe at this tyme to be a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moryall vnto you, for to beware of thoſe which durſt preſume ſo to belye the worde of god, and that vnto kyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges and rulers of the worlde. And in ſtede of goddes worde to fede al men with fables, lyes, and falſe tradycy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. For it teacheth them not onely theyr duety to god &amp; to the hye pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, but alſo of chyldren vnto theyr parentes,<note place="margin">Eph. vi</note> ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes vnto their may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, wyues vnto theyr huſbandes,
<pb facs="tcp:5745:67"/> and how y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> huſbandes agayne ſhuld loue theyr wyues,<note place="margin">Ephe. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> educate theyr chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, prouyde for theyr houſholde, vſe them ſelues towardes theyr ſeuaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, and howe euery degre ſhulde be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haue hym ſelfe one towarde an other Now yf theſe which haue taken vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them to be preachers in tyme paſte, bothe to vs and our fathers, be not approued to be vntrue mynyſters of goddes worde, and falſe lyers therof then beleue not my worke. And yf w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theyr lyeng and falſe doctryne they had hurted the body onely the thyng mought more eaſely be ſuffered. But how can they recompence the iniury done vnto the ſoule of man whiche coulde neuer haue ben redemed,<note place="margin">Ephe. i Col. i. Heb. i.</note> but with the precyous bloode of Chryſte onely, whiche alſo they haue belyed. Who ſoeuer thynke I wryte truely let them beleue the truthe. But for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſatyſfyeng of their myndes, I deſyre them to ſerche the ſcryptures, which
<pb facs="tcp:5745:68"/> I doubte not ſhalbe a wytneſſe vnto me that I haue wrytten the trouthe. And ye that haue receyued the name of Chryſt and are called chriſtiens, I teſtefye vnto you that ye are bounde alſo to receyue his doctryne (whiche is his holy goſpell) or els ye haue a name in vayne, as for the decrees de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretales, conſtitucions, and tradici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of men, and the rules of Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicke Dominicke, Auſtyn, Fraunces or any of them all ye ought to gyue no ferther credence vnto them then they agre with the ſcripture and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyte word of god, of the which word, I requyre and exhorte all men not to be reders &amp; herers onely but alſo fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers therof. For yf any man here the worde and do it not, he is lyke vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to a man that beholdeth his bodely face in a glaſſe,<note place="margin">Iaco. i,</note> for as ſone as he hath loked on hym ſelfe he goeth his way, &amp; forgetteth immediatly what his fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyon was. But who ſo loketh in the
<pb facs="tcp:5745:68"/> perfyte law of lybertye &amp; contynueth therin, yf he be not a forgetfull herer but a doer of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worke, the ſame ſhall be happy in his dede. Theſe are not myne owne wordes, but the godly wordes &amp; counſell of ſaynt Iames (y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apoſtle of Chryſt.) And for becauſe ye ſhall not thynke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> I haue attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in this my worke to entyſe your hertes from deuocyon &amp; to ſet you at lyberty to do what euyll ye lyſt. (as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſclaunderers of goddes worde haue reported of other men.) I praye you to lerne a leſſon or .ii. more of ſaynt Iames &amp; of other holy men y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye may know what pure deuocyon is, &amp; how ye ought to pray &amp; aſke in fayth, and knowe what lyberty ye haue by the goſpell &amp; word of god. Pure deuocyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and vndefiled before god y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father is this to viſyte y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dleſſe &amp; wydowes in aduerſyte,<note place="margin">Iaco. i.</note> and to kepe your ſelues vnſpotted of the worlde.<note place="margin">Iaco. i.</note> If any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lacke wyſdome let hym aſke it of god
<pb facs="tcp:5745:69"/> whiche gyueth to all men indyffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently, and caſteth no man in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tethe and it ſhall be gyuen hym. But let hym aſke in faythe and wauer not, for he y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wauereth is lyke the wawes of the ſee toſt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wynde and caryed with vyolence, neyther let that man thynke he ſhall receyue any thyng of the lorde. A waueryng mynded man is vnſtable in all his wayes. Dauyd ſayth put y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> thi truſt in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord &amp; be do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yng good,<note place="margin">Pſal. xxxvi.</note> ſo ſhal he gyue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thy herts deſyre. This ſayeng of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ꝓphet agre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which ſay y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture &amp; new lernyng (as they cal it) ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at liberty to do what they lyſt but they are enemyes to Chriſt &amp; his doctrine y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſo haue taught the people, &amp; their ygnorau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is moch to be lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted whiche beleued the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Dauyd byd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth you to do good, &amp; abſteyne from euyl, &amp; ſo do al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> places of ſcripture likewyſe exhorte you, for where ye haue herd y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it ſhalbe geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you of god
<pb facs="tcp:5745:69"/> the father what ſoeuer ye aſke in his ſonnes name. Thynke ye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſe dothe perteyne to ſuche as be euyll doers, and contynewe ſtyll in wyckedneſſe, no truly.<note place="margin">ii. thi. ii</note> Saynt Paule ſayeth let him that calleth on the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me of Chryſt departe from iniquite. Wherfore I counſayll you to folowe the exortacyon of Paule, Peter, Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, and Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and ſuche as were Chriſtes apoſtles and dyſcyples, lea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uynge vnto vs a memoryall of their lyuyng, whoſe doctryne accordeth w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theyr mayſters, and is approued for holy ſcrypture, theyr lernynge is no newe lernynge. It is aboue a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſande yeres olde, and yf that be not olde ynough, then I pray you to loke vpon the doctryne of Dauyd, Eſaye Ieromy, and ſuche as were the holy prophetes, &amp; compare their documen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes, and lyuyng with the apoſtles, &amp; ſe howe all they agree togyther in Chriſt, and if ye paſſe ſo moche vpon
<pb facs="tcp:5745:70"/> the nombre of yeres, becauſe ye ſaye ye wyll kepe the olde lawe and olde facyons, I am ſure they may be your fathers great grauntfathers. Wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore ſaye not y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye wyl do as your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers haue don. For as I haue wryt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten before ther were crafty ſcole may<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſters that taught the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vntrue leſſons, but many perceyued them whiche co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ueted to ſe the dayes that we ſe. Wherfore yf ye deny the doctryne of the apoſtles and prophetes ye deny Chryſtes goſpell,<note place="margin">Luce. x.</note> yf ye deny his holy goſpell ye deny Chryſt hym ſelfe. If ye ſaye ye deny not Chryſt it is not trewe, as longe as ye ſclaundre his worde, callyng it newe lernyng, ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king euyl of the teachers and reders of it. And ye your ſelues refuſynge bothe to rede and here his godly wyl declared vnto you in his ſcryptures. Wherfore yf ye wyll be membres of his churche, helpe to repayre agayne the lordes temple, inbrace his ſcryp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<pb facs="tcp:5745:70"/> herken vnto his voyce, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them which calleth you vnto him. And when ye are come folow hym in doynge the workes of charyte which belong vnto fayth, that ye maye here theſe confortable and ioyful wordes of Chryſt. Come hether ye bleſſed of my father,<note place="margin">mat. xxv</note> enheryte ye the kyngdom whiche is prepared for you from the begynnyng of the worlde. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>¶Finis.</trailer>
            <closer>¶God ſaue the kyng.</closer>
            <trailer>¶Cum priuilegio.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:5745:71"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <q>HONY SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
                  <figDesc>printer's device of John Wayland</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>¶Imprynted at London by Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Waylande with in Temple barre, at the ſygne of the blewe garland. Anno. M.D.xxxviii. he. xvi. day of Octobre.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:5745:71"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
